<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cms>
	<content name="what-we-believe">
		<title>What We believe</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/what-we-believe.jpg" />
			Although the whole Bible must be taken as the full description of what a follower of the Lord Jesus believes, here is a short list of some of the most important truths in the Word of God which we believe with all our hearts.
			<strong>THE BIBLE</strong> We believe in the Bible as the Word of God. It is inspired by God, meaning that he gave his truth to holy men who, though they wrote in their own words, yet perfectly wrote what God wanted (2 Pet. 1:20-21). <br /><br /> We have found the Bible to be exactly what we need, and all that we need to be our guide for salvation, and for every area of our Christian life and testimony (2 Tim. 3:16-17).
			<strong>GOD</strong>We believe that there is one God, the Creator of all. Yet the Bible also tell us that this one God has shown himself to us in three persons: Father, Son, and Holy Spirit (1 Cor. 8:6). <br /><br />Romans 1:20 tells us that "the invisible things of [God] from the creation of the world are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead; so that they are without excuse." In other words, God's nature can be seen in our universe. Like time (future, present, past) and space (length, breadth, height), and matter, God is three in one. As an illustration, 1 x 1 x 1 = 1.
			<strong>THE LORD JESUS CHRIST</strong>We believe that the Lord Jesus Christ is fully God, and that at the same time - since he was born in Bethlehem - he is also true Man, begotten by the Holy Spirit and born of a virgin. He is perfect, and it is impossible for him to sin (John 1:1; Phil. 2:6; Mt. 1:23-25; 1 John 3:5).
			<strong>SIN AND SALVATION</strong>We believe that God rules over all things yet has given his creatures a will so they may choose either to obey or not to obey the gospel (2 Thess. 1:8).<br /><br />We believe that every part of our human nature has been damaged through the sin in the Garden of Eden, where our first parents, Adam and Eve, were tempted and deceived by Satan. All are born sinners (except the Lord Jesus) and all are guilty sinners for choosing to sin against God (Rom. 3:23; 5:12).<br /><br />We believe that Satan is a real and personal devil, the arch-enemy of God and man. We know he will not win; his doom is described in the book of the Revelation (Rev. 20:20).<br /><br />Because of the damage that sin has done to us, we believe that all sinners are unable to be saved from eternal punishment by their own righteousness or by good works which they may do (Gen. 3; Rom. 3:23; Eph. 2:8-9).<br /><br />But God, who so loves the world, has found the way to save us through the finished work of Christ on the cross of Calvary. By his sacrifice, Christ has made possible, to all who believe, a complete and eternal redemption (Rom 3:24; Eph. 1:7).
			<strong>CHRIST'S RESURRECTION AND EXALTING</strong>God proved he was satisfied with the work of Christ when he raised the Lord Jesus bodily from the dead and seated him at his right hand in heaven (Eph. 1:20-21).<br /><br />There God has declared the Lord Jesus Christ to be the only Head of the Church (Eph. 1:20-23; Col. 1:18). He is the Lord of the individual (John 13:13), the High Priest over the House of God (Heb. 7:20-28; 10:21), the Advocate on behalf of His people (1 John 2:1), and the Judge of all (Acts 17:31).<br /><br />We believe in the immediate and eternal salvation of every person who truly believes on Christ. This means that we rest, by faith, on His finished work because we believe it is the only righteous way on which a holy God can forgive sins (Rom. 4:4-5; 1 Jn. 5:12).
			<strong>BAPTISM</strong>We also believe that all who are saved are to give the witness of a good conscience before God, being baptized by immersion (Acts 8:36-39).
			<strong>HEAVEN AND HELL</strong>Because Christ is raised, we also believe in the certain hope of the bodily resurrection of the just and the unjust. The Bible teaches the eternal security of the saved and their everlasting blessedness with the Lord (1 Thess. 4:17). The Bible also teaches the everlasting, conscious punishment of the lost (Rev. 20:15).
			<strong>THE HOLY SPIRIT</strong>We believe that all who by faith receive the Lord Jesus Christ as Saviour are instantly born again of the Holy Spirit, indwelt by Him, and by the same Holy Spirit are baptized into the one Body of Christ, the Church (1 Cor. 12:12-14).
			<strong>THE CHURCH</strong>Because the early Church met together and "continued steadfastly in the apostle's doctrine and fellowship, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers," we believe that this is God's pattern for the Church today (Acts 2:42).
			<strong>THE LORD'S COMING</strong>According to his promise, we believe in the personal, imminent, and premillennial coming of the Lord to the air to rapture, or catch away, the Church (1 Thess. 4:13-17). "And so shall we always be with the Lord."
			<strong>THE UNENDING KINGDOM</strong>We also believe that, at the end of human history, Christ will come to establish His kingdom visibly on earth and to reign in righteousness (2 Thess. 1:6-10). After this he will set up the Great White Throne judgment in the heavens for the judgment of "the dead, small and great" (Rev. 20:15). Then the present heavens and earth will pass away and a new heaven and earth will be formed in which righteousness shall dwell and the eternal Day of God will be ushered in (2 Pet. 3:10-13). <br /><br />
			<em>"Even so, come, Lord Jesus!"</em>
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-worlds-most-famous-sentence-explained">
		<title>The World's Most Famous Sentence Explained</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/WorldinHands.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">For God so loved the world<br />that He gave His only begotten Son,<br />that whoever believes in Him<br />should not perish but have<br />everlasting life. (John 3:16)</strong>
			The reason this is arguably the world's most well-known sentence is because it is the best known line in the best-selling book of all time - the Bible. Read on to see how this special message is intended for individuals just like you and me.<br />
			<strong>God's message to us</strong>The sentence is one of the most famous statements in the world. It has been called "the Bible in a nutshell" because it plainly gives us God's basic message.
			<br /><br />It tells the story of a thrilling space mission unlike anything undertaken before or since.<br />This rescue operation was so remarkable that it dwarfs the amazing accomplishments of humanity.
			<br /><br />How clear and simple! The sentence contains only twenty-five words (in our English translation). The first twelve have to do with God; the last twelve are about us; and the middle word is the "Son."
			<br /><br />God's love moved him to provide a way to save us from our sin and from death, its consequence, requiring his Son to travel through space in the other direction, entering our world as a man. Why?
			<br /><br />Because sin had separated us from God, the source of all life. We were doomed to perish, "For the wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord" (Romans 6:23).
			<br /><br />How was this gift provided? The Lord Jesus volunteered to take the sinners' place and die for us. By agreeing with God that we deserved the death which Jesus died, and accepting his salvation simply as a gift from God, this sentence says we will not perish. But what does it mean to perish?
			<br /><br />Tragically, it means you will never fulfill the purpose for which you were created, and be forever separated from God. But there is no need! "Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and you shall be saved" (Acts 16:31).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-simple-gospel">
		<title>The Simple Gospel</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/IAM.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">WHY YOU CAN'T MAKE IT TO HEAVEN BY BEING GOOD OR DOING GOOD</strong>Let's get one thing straight at the beginning. Good works are a good thing. And seeking to obey the Ten Commandments or any other part of the Word of God is a good thing. Everything we say in the rest of this article is not meant to demean being good or doing good.
			<br /><br />However, there is a big difference between doing good as the way to earn eternal life and doing good as the way to show my thanks for having received God's gift of life.
			<br /><br />Most people have been convinced (often by religious leaders) that the way to heaven is by doing good works, or being especially religious, by living according to the Ten Commandments or by keeping the Golden Rule. I'm sure you have heard that. Maybe you believe it. But did you know that the Bible says nothing of the kind. In fact, it says just the opposite! Listen to this:
			<br /><br />"For by grace you are saved through faith; and that not of yourselves: it is the gift of God: not of works, lest anyone should boast" (Ephesians 2:8:9).
			<br /><br />Again we read in the Bible, "Not by works of righteousness which we have done, but according to his mercy he saved us" (Titus 3:5).
			<br /><br />Here's another: "But to him that works not, but believes on him that justifies the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness" (Romans 4:5).
			<br /><br />Let's look at three basic problems with the idea that our goodness can save us.
			<strong>WHO IS GOOD ENOUGH?</strong>First, no one can be good enough or do enough good works to satisfy a perfect God. Compared to God's righteousness, the Bible says, "We are all as an unclean thing, and all our righteousnesses are as filthy rags" (Isaiah 64:6).<br /><br />You may say, I'm not as bad as other people - I don't do what they do. That may be true. But what have you done? For the Bible says, "Whoever shall keep the whole law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all" (James 2:10).<br />Every close relationship is based on being honest. God wants us to be honest with him.
			<br /><br />One of the the things said against Jesus by his enemies - the religious leaders of his day - was that he seemed to spend so much time with people who were obvious sinners. One day they asked his disciples why he did that.
			<br /><br />When Jesus overheard this, he said an amazing thing: If you saw a doctor with sick people, what would you say? "What is that doctor doing with those sick people? Doesn't he know they are sick?" But that's just the point, said Jesus. Those who are well don't need a physician; it's the ones who are sick. Then he explained what he meant: "I didn't come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance." You can read this in the Bible in Mark 2:16-17.
			<br /><br />So you see it isn't a good idea to pretend you're good. You will disqualify yourself from Jesus' help. And he is the very one we need! How important it is to give up our arguments in trying to justify ourselves and agree with God's assessment of our problem. We are guilty sinners - exactly the ones whom Jesus died to save.
			<strong>DOES GOD OWE YOU?</strong>Seeking to earn heaven also puts us in a very strange situation because it supposedly puts God into our debt. That's just what is written in the book of Romans: "Now to him that works is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt" (Rom. 4:4). Will you tell God when you stand before him that he owes you a place in heaven?
			<br /><br />You surely don't mean that after all he has given you - every breath you have breathed, every mouthful you have eaten, every moment you have lived - that because you took a little of what he gave you in the first place and gave it back to him, that now he owes you?
			<br /><br />No, the Bible makes it clear that salvation is a gift - unearned, undeserved, paid for by another. "For the wages of sin is death (wages are deserved payment); but the gift of God (undeserved and freely given) is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord" (Romans 6:23).
			<strong>WHY THEN DID JESUS DIE?</strong>If heaven is within the reach of all those who do their best, why did Jesus die? We don't have to guess what the answer might be. The Bible, God's Word, is full of statements that tell us why he died. Here are a few of them:
			<br />"For when we were yet without strength, in due time Christ died for the ungodly &hellip; But God commends his love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us" (Romans 5:6, 8).
			<br /><br />"I delivered unto you first of all that which I also received, how that Christ died for our sins according to the scriptures; and that he was buried, and that he rose again the third day according to the scriptures" (1 Cor. 15:3-4).
			<br />"Neither is there salvation in any other: for there is no other name under heaven given among men, by which we must be saved" (Acts 4:12).
			<br /><br />The best thing any of us can do is to discover God's answer to our problem. It is simply this: "Repent and believe the gospel" (Mark 1:15). Agree with God about the problem - our personal sin. Then accept his answer by believing the good news - Christ died for you and will pay your debt in full if you will accept his free gift of everlasting life. Why not ask him now?
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-good-news-as-simple-as-it-gets">
		<title>The Good News - as simple as it gets</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/sharing-the-good-news.jpg" />
			<em>Some people, when they hear God's good news simply described, object to it for that very reason. "There must be more to it," they say. "That's too simple."</em>
			<br /><br />We have to understand two things here. First we must understand the difference between a thing that is simple to understand and something that is simple to enjoy.
			<br /><br />For example, do you understand all about light? Even the scientists don't understand light! They still can't decide whether it is a particle or a wave. But do you have to understand it to enjoy it? No. Just turn on the light.
			<br /><br />Do you have to understand all about digestion to enjoy a good meal or understand electricity so you can use it? Thankfully, no.
			<br /><br />So it is with the good news from God. It is very complex to understand. You will see that if you look at the book of Romans, for example. But to make it available to everyone, God made the good news as simple as drinking water or eating food to enjoy (see Psalm 34:8).
			<br /><br />The second thing we should understand is the difference between "simple" and "easy". The way of salvation is simple to grasp but it is not easy to obey. Because to obey the good news we must first agree with the bad news.

			<br /><br />
			<em>Here is the good news of God in four sentences from the Bible:</em>
			<br /><br />1. "All have sinned" (Romans 3:23). That means that everyone born into the world has done or thought things that are against God. God has told us, "Do not steal" and we have taken things that were not ours. He has told us, "Do not lie" and we have said things that were not true.
			<br /><br />He has said, "Do not commit adultery" and Jesus explained what this meant. If you look at someone to lust after that person, you have already committed adultery in your heart (Matthew 5:28).
			<br /><br />In the same way, Jesus said, If you hate someone, God puts murder down beside your name. Sin is a fact before it is an act. And we are all guilty before God in our thoughts. He knows every sin we have ever committed.
			<br /><br />There are many other Bible verses like: "The thought of foolishness is sin" (Proverbs 24:9). Or "To the one that knows to do good, and does not do it, to him it is sin" (James 4:17). Yes, we're guilty, alright.
			<br /><br />2. "The soul that sins dies" (Ezekiel 18:4). That is the penalty for sin. To put it another way, our sin separates us from God (Isaiah 59:2) who is the source of life. Without him, we're doomed.
			<br /><br />In the Bible, death is not the end. Death is separation. That's why we read: "It is appointed unto men once to die, but after this the judgment" (Heb 9:27). You have noticed that everyone dies, sooner or later. But when we whisper, "They're gone!" where have they gone?
			<br /><br />The Bible says there are only two destinations for people who leave this earth - heaven or hell. Jesus made it clear that these places exist (you can read about it in the Bible in Luke 16) and once earth's choice has been made, there is no changing it in eternity. That's why your decision now is so very important.
			
			<br /><br />3. "Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners" (1 Timothy 1:15). Who ever heard such good news! There is a Saviour who has come to rescue sinners like us. He is the only Saviour. No world religion offers anything like this. They basically tell you to save yourself - something the Bible says we cannot do (see Titus 3:5).
			<br /><br />But this is the reason Jesus came to planet earth. He came for you and me. When he died on the cross just outside Jerusalem, God paid for our sin. Here is what the Bible says: "Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the [satisfaction] for our sins" (1 John 4:10).
			<br /><br />But the real question is: How can we get in on this? How can we be saved from our sin and be ready to meet God? That brings us to sentence number four.
			<br /><br />4. "Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ and you shall be saved" (Acts 16:31).
			<br /><br />There is no doubt about it. If you believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, what does the verse say will happen? You SHALL be saved. What an amazing promise!
			<br /><br />Jesus not only died; three days later he arose from his grave and was seen by many witnesses, including some of his enemies like Saul, a man who killed Jesus' followers. Saul then knew the truth and became a true follower of the Lord Jesus, too. Afterwards he wrote much of the Bible.
			<br /><br />So what does it mean to believe on the Lord Jesus? It means to put all your confidence in him, to entrust your whole case to him. It means to ask him to be your personal Saviour by making full payment for your sin.
			<br /><br />Believe that you are the sinner Jesus died to save. Receive him now as your personal Saviour "and you shall be saved."
			<br /><br />Then send us an email and tell us about it. If you include your mailing address, we'll send you some helpful materials that explain how to be a follower of the Lord Jesus.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="two-of-lifes-most-important-words">
		<title>Two of Life's Most Important Words</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/SavedFaith.jpg" />
			Two of the most important words we can ever understand are found in one sentence from the Bible. They are the first and last words in the book of Acts chapter 16 and verse 31, "Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ and you shall be saved."
			<br /><br /><strong>THE MEANING OF "SAVED"</strong><br /><br />Let's begin at the end of the sentence and ask what it means to be saved. Of course we understand that being saved in natural terms always means being saved from something. If you are struggling in the water, you need to be saved from drowning. If you are in a burning building, you need to be saved from the fire.
			<br /><br />From what does the Bible say we need to be saved? You may not feel you are in any danger at all at the moment. Yet God's Word tells us that Christ Jesus came into the world to save us (see 1 Timothy 1:15). Save us from what?
			<br /><br />When Jesus was to be born, an angel from heaven explained that his name was to be Jesus, meaning "Jehovah (God) is salvation." The angel said, "And [Mary] shall bring forth a son, and you shall call his name JESUS: for he shall save his people from their sins" (Matthew 1:21).
			<br /><br />So there is the answer. We need to be saved from our sins. We need to be saved from the judgment which our sins deserve. And we need to be saved from the grip that sin has on our hearts and minds, from the damage that sin does to our lives, our relationships, and everything else it touches. Yes, we need to be saved.
			<br /><br />But if the way to be saved, according to the statement at the top, is to believe on the Lord Jesus, what exactly does it mean to believe?
			
			<strong>THE MEANING OF "BELIEVE"</strong>Believing the facts about God is a good start, but it is not enough. The Apostle James wrote, "You believe that there is one God; you do well: the demons also believe, and tremble" (James 2:19). But it obviously doesn't do the demons any good, does it?
			<br /><br />There is more to believing than accepting facts in your head. We have an example of some people like this described in the book of John (the fourth book in the New Testament part of the Bible). We read this:
			<br /><br />Now when [Jesus] was in Jerusalem at the passover, in the feast day, many believed in his name, when they saw the miracles which he did. But Jesus did not commit himself unto them, because he knew all men, and needed not that any should testify of man: for he knew what was in man. (John 2:23-25).
			<br /><br />These people believed some things about Jesus because they were impressed with his miracles. But Jesus - notice the words - did not commit himself to them because they did not commit themselves to him.
			<br /><br />It is possible, for example, to know a great deal about someone, but that is very different from committing yourself to them in marriage, isn't it? In a similar way, the Lord Jesus is asking us to do something more than simply agreeing with him about certain things. He is asking us to take some very important steps.
			<br /><br />First we are to believe him when he describes the seriousness of our fundamental problem. When the Bible says, "Christ died for our sins," we can only draw one conclusion. If the Lord Jesus Christ died in our place, it means, of course, that our sins deserved the death sentence.
			<br /><br />That is exactly what is written in God's Word. James describes our sin in this way: "When lust has conceived, it brings forth sin: and sin, when it is finished, brings forth death" (James 1:15).
			<br /><br />What a picture! It's as if lust (our strong inward desires for the wrong things) has a baby. Aren't babies cute! And at first our sin might appear to be harmless and cute as well. But then, says James, sin doesn't stay little; it eventually grows up into a monster and kills us!
			<br /><br />Are we prepared to agree with God about this? This the Bible calls repentance - a change of mind that leads to a change of direction in our lives. This is a shocking discovery, I know. Repentance is agreeing with God that I deserve to be executed for my rebellion against him. It is understanding that the horrible death Jesus died was actually my death.
			
			<br /><br />The Lord Jesus wants us to say in our hearts: I have failed in my plans for life. I have sinned against God and broken his law. I want the Lord Jesus to take over now, to save me from my sin, and make me right with God. I can't think of anything that makes more sense, can you?
			<br /><br />So what must you do to be saved? Listen to these important words, "[Jesus] came to his own, and his own [people] did not receive him. But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God, even to those that believe on his name" (John 1:11-12).
			<br /><br />This is helpful, isn't it. Now we have another word that is equal to the real meaning of "believe" - the kind of believing that makes a difference, in fact, that makes all the difference in the world. It is the word "receive."
			<br /><br />To truly believe on the Lord Jesus, then, means that I receive him. If, late at night, a stranger carrying a gun appeared at your door and demanded that you let him into your house, would you? Of course not!
			<br /><br />But if a friend came by, perhaps bringing you a special gift, what would you do? Wouldn't you "receive" them into your house? Of course you would.
			<br /><br />Don't you see that this is also the reason we can trust the Lord Jesus with our our sin problem, our lives, our eternity! Can you not trust the one who willingly gave up all he had and died for you? How can we not love someone like that?
			<br /><br />He stands at your heart's door today. Because he is a perfect gentleman, he will not push his way in. He waits for you to receive him as your Saviour and Lord. It is the only sensible thing to do.
			<br /><br />If you have any questions or if you have received the Lord Jesus and would like some help in your new life, you can write or email us. We'll send you some helpful materials.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="give-it-to-me-straight">
		<title>Give it to Me Straight</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/GUWG-Bible-Path.gif" />
			I don't know about you, but if I visit a doctor when I know something is wrong with me, I ask him to "give it to me straight, Doctor." After all, it's my body and I deserve to have the facts. More than that, I want him to keep it simple. I don't want his explanation given in long medical terms that I don't understand.
			<br /><br />If that's how we feel about our bodies, how serious we should be to hear the truth about our never-dying souls? That's why I want to give the basic message of the Bible for you as straight as I can.
			<strong>HOW IT ALL BEGAN</strong>First, the Bible explains that God made the universe a perfect place and saw that "it was very good." (Genesis 1:31) But in making us, God gave us a will so we would be able to choose. He didn't want toys or machines; he wanted people who could share a loving relationship with him.
			<br /><br />It seemed an ideal situation. There were no wars, funerals, or hospitals; no broken hearts, neglected children or abused wives. There was no shame over wrong words or actions either. The human race was in perfect peace and contentment with the Creator. Who wouldn't want to live in a world like that?
			<strong>WHAT WENT WRONG?</strong>But there was a problem. Some time before (we aren't told when) an angel-servant of God, called Lucifer, wanted to put himself in the place of God. (Isaiah 14:12-15) If fact, he led about one-third of the angels in a rebellion against God. And this trying to replace God with himself is the very sin that the rebel (renamed Satan) taught the human race.
			<br /><br />Why should you do God's will when you can do what you want? Why live to please him when you can live to please yourself? Why not ask as if you are God? But - strange as it seems - this trying to go our own way and find our own pleasure has led the human race in exactly the opposite direction. It has been the reason for all the world's sadness, trouble and death.
			<br /><br />So the sad record reads: "As by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin; and so death passed upon all men, because all have sinned" (Romans 5:12).
			<br /><br />The world, in spite of all its inventions and discoveries, seems to be getting worse. You wonder how long we can carry on like this. And it isn't just others who have the problem. If we're honest, we have to admit we don't do what we should, either. We don't even come up to our own standards, let alone God's. We don't even keep our own New Year's promises.
			
			
			<strong>THE GREAT RESCUE OPERATION</strong>This brings us to the story of Jesus. God, who hates sin and must punish it, also loves his creatures. So he put into action a plan so daring that many people still don't believe it could be true. What he decided to do was to send his own Son, the Lord Jesus, to die in our place.
			<br /><br />Even though he was God, Jesus willingly came to earth to give his life as the payment for our sins. Since our sins deserved death - being separated from God forever - and there are billions of sinners, only a "God-sized" substitute would be enough to pay for all the wrong that we have done by his death. But God, being a spirit, cannot die. So in Jesus, God became a man to die for the sins of his own creatures! Amazing love!
			<br /><br />"For God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoever believes in him should not perish, but have eternal life" (John 3:16).
			<strong>NOW IT'S YOUR TURN</strong>Some people have heard these basic facts before: that we are all sinners; that our sins deserve God's punishment; that God loves sinners even though he hates our sin; and that Jesus died for sinners at the Cross.
			<br /><br />But what many people have never heard (or never understood) is that the Lord Jesus who died for our sins also rose again and "is not far from every one of us," waiting for us to personally receive him as Saviour. (Acts 17:27)
			<br /><br />We each need an experience in our lives like the one that happened to a man in the Bible named Paul. He had grown up in a home where he was taught to hate the name of Jesus. He believed Jesus was a fraud. But one day on a business trip, he discovered for himself that Jesus was who he said he was. Later Paul would write: "The Son of God&hellip; loved me, and gave himself for me." (Galatians 2:20) Just think about it! God's Son left heaven and came to this sorry world for you. He gave his life for you. He willingly paid your debt if you will accept his pardon.
			<br /><br />Simply speak to him from your heart; be honest about your failure. Then ask him to save you from your sins. If you are sincere in wanting him to save you and take over your life, here is his promise:
			<br />"Whoever comes to me I will in no way cast him out."
			<br /><br />Here is another statement from Jesus himself that puts it all together, "Truly, truly, I say to you, whoever hears my word, and believes on the One who sent me, has everlasting life, and shall not come into condemnation; but is already passed from death into life" (John 5:24).
			<br /><br />There is one way of knowing whether this is true or not. You'll know it is true when it happens to you! If you, through reading these Bible verses i) hear the Lord Jesus speaking to you personally, and ii) your heart says "Yes!" to him as your own Saviour from sin, then the Lord himself says that you have everlasting life.
			<br /><br />If you have received him as your Saviour, be sure to thank Him for this new life. And send us an email (with your address) so we can give you some helpful free literature.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="twice-purchased">
		<title>Twice Purchased</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/CryingBoy.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">written by Robert Brown</strong>I began life as a "throw away" child in an orphanage one cold, winter night, the 12th of February, 1944. It was in the stockyard town of South St. Paul, Minnesota. My "given" name was Leonard Allen Boe (aka. Leonard Allen Stenstrom). There are only unanswered questions to fill in the missing pieces of my life or background, my parents or family. In the spring, a young couple from Minneapolis (Roy and Alice Brown) came, sought me out, chose me, purchased me for the price of $55.50, changed my name to Robert Reed Brown, made me their child, and took me home to live with them! I was a "chosen child" they told me &hellip; and I am very thankful for them and for that! But, down inside I was still an unwanted child, thrown away by his mother.
			<br /><br />No matter what you said, how you acted, or what you did, I was still an unwanted child with a lot of questions going unanswered. Who were my real parents? Who were my brothers and sisters? Who was I? Why didn't my mother want me? How could she give me up? Where did I fit in? Where did I belong? From the very earliest age I knew something was missing but I just didn't know what it was.
			<br /><br />My foster parents raised me in a nominal Christian home. They had me baptized. We went to church every Sunday. I sang in the choir, was an altar boy, played the trumpet for special services, was confirmed, joined the church, and took communion. I was a religious boy, but something was still missing, and I was still searching.
			<br /><br />I started smoking at age seven and drinking at thirteen. I began racing cars and motorcycles, fighting, and chasing all the wrong kinds of girls, only to find that none of these things could fill the emptiness that I felt inside.
			<br /><br />I attended the University of Minnesota and studied philosophy and psychology, but found no answers there - only more questions, and more people who were themselves looking for answers.
			<br /><br />In October 1964, I was married and went on active duty with the U.S. Navy. For the first time in my life I had a family that was my own. JoAnne, my highschool sweetheart, and I had three beautiful girls. I was a success in my work, and traveled the world. I was realizing a lifelong dream, but the emptiness was still with me. Year by year, my attempts to fill that emptiness by continually grasping for things that the world offered, was taking a toll on my life in every area that was important to me.
			<br /><br />By January 1975, I had lost my wife and family, my home and friends, and was living in the Bachelor Chiefs Barracks at a naval station in Pennsylvania. There was a strange fellowship of empty equals within that barracks! There seemed no end to the alcohol, partying, and girls that drifted in and out of the rooms at all hours, day and night. The only two "quite respectable" rooms were those of the local NIS agent, and the one across the hall from mine (which turned out to be a place where abortions were performed). This was a real collection of disillusioned, lost souls if ever there was one, and it all served to accentuate the realization of my own emptiness.
			
			<br /><br />Then God brought an old shipmate, Charlie Glass, back into my life. We used to drink and party together, but since then Charlie and his wife Rae Ann had gotten saved. One day Charlie asked me if I knew for sure that when I died, I would go to heaven. I replied that I didn't think that anyone could know that. He shared 1 John 5:13 with me, and gave me the tract, Am I Going to Heaven? I failed the test in that tract and set out to prove Charlie wrong from the Bible. I failed again. Over a period of time, Charlie and others shared with me how the emptiness I felt was my separation from God on account of my sin. They spoke of how God had sent His Son, Jesus, to pay the penalty that I owed for that sin by dying in my place on the cross of Calvary. Through these and many other patient, loving Christians at a local assembly, I saw that what they had told me was true.
			<br /><br />On November 30, 1975, in the attic of a farmhouse in northern Pennsylvania, on a Chapel men's deer hunting trip, I accepted Jesus Christ as my Lord and Saviour. That night I found that a throwaway child worth only $55.50 in this world was worth the very best that God had to offer - His Son Jesus! He had loved me, chosen me, changed my name, purchased me, and took me out of my life of sin, and one day plans to take me home to be with Him forever in heaven. Twice loved, twice chosen, twice purchased, twice adopted, and now a child of God. An heir and joint heir with Christ - a child of the King!
			<br /><br />Since accepting Christ as my Lord and Saviour, the Lord has given me back my wonderful wife JoAnne and family, reestablished my home, taught me about Himself and His plan for my life. He has built me up spiritually, and allowed me to serve Him. My continuing burden is to see others find the real inner peace and joy that I have found. And that only comes from having a personal relationship with God through His Son, Jesus Christ.
			<br /><br />Psalm 40 says: "I waited patiently for the Lord; and He inclined unto me, and heard my cry. He brought me up also out of an horrible pit, out of the miry clay, and set my feet upon a rock [Jesus], and established my goings. And He hath put a new song in my mouth, even praise unto our God &hellip; "All of this He has done for me, and I pray that as the psalm finishes: " &hellip; many shall see it, and fear, and shall trust in the Lord!"
			<br /><br />Originally published in <em>UPLOOK Magazine</em>
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="rescue-at-pearl-harbor">
		<title>Rescue at Pearl Harbor</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Warplanes.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Ned Varney</strong>
			I was brought up in the Roman Catholic religion and was an altar boy in the church of that faith. I tell you this because I want you to know that I had a "Christian" upbringing. Such religion did me little good in the years ahead.
			<br /><br />When I was about fourteen years old, after graduating from junior high, I went on to high school. The first week I was there, I brought a knife to school to show my friend. It was one that my older brother, who was a professional knife-thrower in a carnival, had given me the last time he had come home. As I was showing it, the teacher saw it and demanded it from me. My short temper flared up and I said, "You want it? Then take it!" and saying so, I threw it at him. I missed, but, needless to say, was expelled from school. It was the end of my formal education. Now I would begin my education on the street.
			<br /><br />I began to work with my brother-in-law who retrieved cases of contraband whiskey that had been dumped overboard after high-speed chases by the Coast Guard. We then delivered these to the parties to whom they had been consigned. That went on for awhile &hellip; until we were caught! My brother-in-law was convicted and went to jail and I was released because I was still a minor.
			<br /><br />My parents were disgusted with me and I was told to leave their home. I made my way to New York City with ten cents in my pocket. There I found myself standing on a street corner, wondering what to do, when a man came up to me and said, "Say kid, do you want to earn half a buck?" Shaking my head yes, I was handed a potato. He told me to put it in the tailpipe of a car that was parked nearby. Naively, I did what I was told to do, not knowing that the car was an unmarked police car. I stayed around that neighborhood for the rest of that day. The same man came back later and gave me another half dollar, congratulating me on a fine job. This was my first tie-in with the underworld. Unfortunately, it would not be my last.
			<br /><br />From then on, I became a runner, doing errands for criminals. Then I ran a book (small-time gambling), became a bagman (transporting illegally obtained money), then was a driver. All this did not happen in a short space of time. I gradually had to make myself available, willing, and then able to do what I was told - and to keep my mouth shut.
			<br /><br />In order to support myself in the lean times, I took a job as an orderly in one of the local hospitals. There I met a doctor who took a liking to me and encouraged me to enroll in a nursing course. I did not finish the course completely but accomplished enough to get a certificate to do practical nursing. This came in handy in later days because when the authorities were getting too close, I would hide (as it were) in a hospital and stay there until it was safe to come out and go back to making big money again.
			<br /><br />The most responsible job that I had was as a driver. I drove for three successful bank robberies plus many smaller jobs. After one of these jobs, my friend and I went to Mississippi, his home state. There I drove for a bootlegger, delivering whiskey. While on one of these trips, I was shot and had to have the bullet removed by a local quack. The cost was $7000. There my friend was caught and told all about me so that I had to go into hiding again. I picked Paterson NJ, and found a job in a hospital there.
			<br /><br />One Sunday, I asked to have a date with one of the nurses. She agreed, and took me to a little building which was a place where people came to hear a man talk about God. I shut out the preacher completely. I did not want to hear anything about Him. All I wanted to do was get out of there.
			<br /><br />I still carried my gun with me wherever I went; I was never without it. I even slept with it under my pillow. When she saw it, she told me I should get rid of it. I said I'd rather get rid of her than to lose my best friend - my gun.
			<br /><br />One day, I heard one of the other nurses talking about the police asking questions about some of the help. I knew it was probably about me, so I simply slipped away and went up to my old hometown. There I enlisted in the Army. I chose to go as far away from the States as I could, choosing Hawaii as my duty. While there, I continued to make myself available to the devil, and ran the gambling games where I took a percentage of the pot.
			<br /><br />Then came that fateful day, December 7, 1941, when the Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor. It was swift and sure. I thought my time had come. Death itself seemed to hold no fear for me; but, all of a sudden, something said to me, "Where are you going to spend eternity?" I said, "In hell." Then it came back to me: that was what that preacher back in New Jersey was talking about. Take Christ as your Saviour and spend eternity in heaven. All I had to do was accept Christ as my substitute and all my sins would be washed away. Right there, hiding behind a stone pillar with bombs falling around me, I took Jesus as my own Saviour. My life was changed. I'm not going to say that everything turned out rosy - I still had my old self.
			<br /><br />The Lord put me through some trying times. I was wounded twice in conflict, stranded in enemy territory for twenty-seven days with no food to eat except some Japanese rice that we found. Through it all, He taught me lessons about His grace and truth.
			<br /><br />I tell you this story, not to brag about how bad I was. Instead, I pray that whoever reads this will know that he or she is not too bad a sinner for Christ to save. Paul the apostle could say in 1 Timothy 1:15, "This is a faithful saying and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am chief." You do not have to be as bad as I was to qualify as a sinner, for all have sinned and come short of God's standard. Thank you for letting me say a few words about the Lord who saved me.
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="a-priest-unknown-to-god">
		<title>A Priest Unknown to God</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/PriestHands-Questions.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Joseph Tremblay</strong>
			I was born in Quebec, Canada, in 1924. From my childhood, my parents inculcated in me a great respect for God. I desired intensely to serve Him to the best of my ability and to consecrate myself totally to Him in order to please Him. It was this desire to please Him that motivated my decision to take the Holy Orders of the Roman Catholic Church.
			<br /><br />After several years of study, I was ordained a priest in Rome, Italy. One year later, I was sent as a missionary to Bolivia and Chile where I served for more than thirteen years. I liked the life very much and tried to discharge my responsibilities as well as I could. I enjoyed the friendship of all of my co-workers. Even if they looked with a certain amusement upon my pronounced taste for the study of the Bible, their invitations to share with them the results of my studies evidenced their approval. When they called me "Joe the Bible" I knew that, in spite of the sarcasm in the expression, they envied me. My parishioners also appreciated the ministry of the Word of God, so much so that they organized a club for home Bible studies. I was compelled to give myself to earnest study of the Bible, as much to prepare myself for the improvised home meetings as to prepare my Sunday sermons.
			<br /><br />New Insight into God's Word
			<br /><br />The study of the Bible, which, until that time, had been just a hobby, quickly became a professional obligation. I became aware of the clarity with which certain truths were taught, and, on the other hand, I discovered that nothing at all was written about many dogmas that I had studied. My Bible study revealed that I did not know the Bible. I suggested to my superiors that I might like to go for further studies in the Bible when my turn for vacation arrived. In the meantime, the Jesuits at Antofagasta invited me to teach the Bible at the Normal School of the University which they directed. Notwithstanding my lack of preparation, I accepted the invitation, knowing that this new responsibility would necessitate even more serious study of the Word of God.
			
			<strong>Dethroned Theology</strong>How many hours were consecrated to the preparation of my classes and my sermons! To maintain morale during my studies, I had the habit of listening to music. I had been given a little transistor radio on which I could listen to background music without the bother of changing records. It was thus that one day I became aware that they were religious songs and hymns that were coming through to me on the little radio. I heard the word "Jesus" from time to time while I was reading. But the hymns didn't last long. They were followed by a short Bible reading. The last verse that was read caught my attention: "For He hath made Him to be sin for us, who knew no sin; that we might be made the righteousness of God in Him" (2 Cor. 5:21). It was on this verse that the sermon which followed was based. At first I was tempted to change the station because it was too distracting to listen to someone speaking while trying to study. In addition, I thought to myself: "What could this minister add to me, after all? Me, with all my degrees! I could teach him a thing or two!" After a moment's hesitation, I decided to listen to what he had to say. I learned some of the most wonderful things concerning the Person of Jesus Christ. I was filled with shame, knowing without a doubt that I couldn't have done as well as the one who had preached. It had seemed to me that it was Jesus Himself who had been speaking to me. And how little I knew Him, this Jesus, who nevertheless was the subject of my thoughts, of my studies; I felt that He was far from me. It was the first time that such a feeling concerning Jesus Christ had ever presented itself to me. It was as if all of my being was but emptiness, around which I had erected a structure of principles and theological dogmas, very beautiful, well-constructed, but which hadn't touched my soul, which hadn't changed my being. And in spite of the fact that I continued to study and to gorge myself with reading, praying and meditating, this emptiness became even greater with each day that passed.
			<br /><br />I went on listening to this same radio station, tuning in to every program that I could. I learned that the station was HCJB in Quito. I learned also that it was consecrated to the preaching of the Gospel to the whole world.
			
			<strong>The Free Gift of Salvation</strong>What struck me the most in all that I heard was the insistence that all the credit for the salvation of man was given, not to the one who was saved, but to the Lord Jesus Christ, the only Saviour; that man could boast of nothing, that his works were but filthy rags, that eternal life could be received within the heart only as a free gift to whoever repents of his sins and receives Jesus Christ into his heart and life as personal Saviour.
			<br /><br />All of this was new to me. It was contrary to the theology I had been taught: that heaven and eternal life are gained by means of one's merit, faithfulness, charity, and sacrifices. And this is what I had been working at for so many years! But what was the result of my efforts? As I considered this question, I said to myself: "I'm not any further ahead. If I commit a mortal sin, I'll go to hell if I die in that state. My theology has taught me that salvation is by works and sacrifices. I discovered in the Bible a free salvation. My theology gives me no assurance of salvation; the Bible offers me that assurance. I'm confused. Perhaps I should stop listening to those evangelical programs!" This battle in me was taking on alarming proportions. I suffered in my body and in my heart: headaches, insomnia, fear of hell. I had no desire to celebrate mass nor to listen to confessions.
			<br /><br />But God continued to speak to me in the solitude of my anguished heart. So many questions surged up in my spirit. The Word of God came to my rescue, spreading a refreshing balm upon my fevered emotions. "For God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in Him should not perish, but have everlasting life" (John 3:16). "For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God; being justified freely by His grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus" (Rom. 3:23-24). "For the wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord" (Rom. 6:23). Many other texts came to mind, texts that I now knew because I had heard them often on the radio.
			<strong>A Sermon That Breaks My Heart</strong>The light dawned in my heart when I least expected it. It was my turn to preach in my parish. For that Sunday I had chosen as my theme: "Religious Hypocrisy," and availed myself of the Bible text: "Not every one that saith unto Me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of My Father which is in heaven. Many will say to Me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in Thy name? and in Thy name have cast out devils? and in Thy name done many wonderful works? And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you; depart from Me, ye that work iniquity" (Matt. 7:21-23).
			<br /><br />I knew my parishioners. I wanted to draw their attention to the vainglory manifested by certain persons with respect to their good works, forgetting that very often these good works camouflaged a corrupt heart. As I delivered my message, I was conscious that the Word of God was coming back to me. It was thus that, while I was giving my message, someone else was speaking in my heart and preaching a sermon to me. I thought that, because I was religious and a priest, I was better than all those who were listening to me. And yet, to me also, this word would resound one day in my ears: "I never knew you: depart from Me." I heard my own arguments against this condemnation: "How is it possible, my God, that You will not know me? Am I not Your priest? Am I not religious? Look at all the sacrifices I have made for You: the years of study, the separation from my parents and my country, my vows of poverty, obedience and chastity, consecrating to You all my riches, my will, my body even, in order to better serve You. And You will say to me that You never knew me? I've baptized children by the hundreds, I've listened to all sorts of confessions, I've comforted so many tearful, discouraged souls, I've suffered cold, loneliness, contempt, ingratitude, threats. I'm ready even to give my life for You." But in spite of all the arguments that I presented to God, the same condemnation continued: "I never knew you."
			<br /><br />I was at the end of arguments, at the end of my strength. The parishioners also sensed the approaching storm. And the storm broke. The tears prevented me from continuing my sermon. When confronted with this terrible frustration of my whole life purpose, facing my sins and the condemnation of God, it was too much for me to bear. I took refuge in my office. And there, on my knees, I waited until calm returned. Where could I turn now? Perhaps my theology would save me, if I returned to it and faithfully followed all its dogmas. But that theology had already begun to experience disorder, change, destruction. My thoughts turned to my friends. But they were in the same situation as I. Trust in myself? I could no longer count on my good works. I was in a state of complete exhaustion, depressed and discouraged. This was the moment God was waiting for, to offer me His grace.
			
			<strong>Jesus Stands at the Door</strong>During all my reflections, God applied His Word to my soul's searching: "For by grace are ye saved through faith; and that not of yourselves: it is the gift of God: not of works, lest any man should boast" (Eph. 2:8-9). It was here that I understood my error and the reason for God's rejection. I had been trying to save myself by my works; God wanted to save me by grace. Someone else had already taken care of my sins and of the judgment attached to them. This someone was Jesus Christ. It was for this that He died on the cross. I remembered the words of Jesus: "Come unto Me, all ye that labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest" (Matt. 11:28). I understood that I must go to Jesus if I wanted to have the assurance of salvation and peace of soul. I had the intention of asking Him: "But where are You, Jesus, so that I might cling to You?" But even before this cry of impatience arose in my heart, I remembered another word that I had heard: "Behold, I stand at the door, and knock: if any man hear My voice, and open the door, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he with Me" (Rev. 3:20).
			<br /><br />Now I knew where Jesus was. He was closer than I had thought. And I hurried to invite Him to enter into my heart, without taking the time to ask permission of any man. "Come in, Lord Jesus; come into my heart. Be its Master, O Beloved Saviour!" At that moment I knew that I was freed from the punishment that had menaced me for so long. I was saved, pardoned. I had eternal life. God had begun His work in me.
			
			<br /><br />What happened after that? At first I continued my priestly service as best I could. But little by little I began to feel like a stranger in that position. I realized that the grace that had saved me was going to enter into conflict with the "works" of the position in which I was trying to live. I was happy because I had the assurance of my salvation. But I was stifled in a setting in which I was pushed to do good works in order to merit salvation. Salvation, I had; therefore, all of these works began to be put aside, one after the other. All that interested me was Jesus Christ, who He was and what He had done. I abandoned the subjects prepared in advance by the liturgical organization of the diocese, in order to devote all of my efforts to the Person and work of my beloved Saviour, presenting Him as such to my bewildered parishioners, confused but often edified. I asked to be released from my functions as a parish priest since I could no longer preach that which contradicted the Word of God. My superiors accepted my resignation, though they couldn't understand why I wanted to leave. They had, in fact, treated me very well. As far as they were concerned, I lacked nothing. This was true, as far as food, clothing, housing, etc., were concerned. But now I had the assurance of my salvation. Christ was now my Master. He would therefore take it upon Himself to continue the work begun, since He never half-does His work.
			<br /><br /><br />I returned to Quebec in 1965 for an extended period of rest. Shortly after, I was visited by evangelical Christians. How did they know of my interest in the Word of God? They were frank with me: my name had been given to them by the personnel of HCJB. However, even if I found their conversation very edifying, I didn't give myself wholly to them. I didn't want to fall into another theological system, having been suppressed for years by the system into which I had been born and in which I had lived for forty years. Nevertheless I prayed to the Lord to find me brothers and sisters to whom I could join myself, so that I wouldn't feel so alone. I knew the experience of the first Christians, according to the report given in Acts 2:42. Was it possible that Christians still met together in our day in order to remember the Lord, while awaiting His return? God, who had provided for the salvation of my soul would provide again.
			<br /><br /><br />My superiors in Montreal invited me to replace a Professor of Theology in a college in Rouyn. I accepted, since it would be only for a few months. The subject I was given to teach was: "The Church." I was given access to all of the books that would be necessary for the preparation of my classes, but I prepared using only the Bible. I explained to the students what the Church is, according to the Bible. I admit that I myself had difficulty in understanding what I was teaching. It was such a contrast with the hierarchical church in which I was still found. One day I learned from the newspaper that a television program was to be presented having as its subject: "The Church." I recorded the program in order to use it in my classes, and discovered that the subject was treated from what the Bible taught. I was so impressed by the similarity between the presentation by this unknown person (whom I later learned was an evangelical Christian) and my own, that I sent a note of thanks to the preacher, Mr. Gaston Jolin, inviting him to come to see me, if this were possible. He came, and I recognized in him someone who knew the Lord. After several visits, he invited me to his home to spend Sunday with his family. On the occasion of that visit, I attended a Remembrance of the Lord service for the first time. I recognized in this service that which was described in 1 Corinthians 11 and realized that God had answered my prayer, having shown me that Christians in our day do indeed meet together as a local church to remember the Lord while awaiting His return (1 Cor. 11:26).
			<br /><br />Shortly after, I wrote to my superiors in Montreal, announcing to them that I had found my family and requesting that they obtain for me a dispensation from all the vows I had made to the Roman Catholic Church since I no longer considered myself a member. My life now belonged to the Lord and its direction was henceforth under His control. It was thus that the Lord liberated me, not only from my sins, not only from His condemnation, but also from every system of man which burdens and suppresses.
			<br /><br /><br />Since I have been born again by the grace of God, my wife and I spend much of our time telling others about Christ, the One and only Saviour and Lord who can save perfectly "all those who come to God by Him" (Heb. 7:25). God has also allowed me to use the same means of communication that brought me to Him, that is, radio and television.
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-hard-way-home">
		<title>The Hard Way Home</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/HardWayHome-cropped.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Carol Stevens</strong>
			I was born in Washington, DC, April 12, 1954. My mother was German; my father was Welsh. I grew up in a middle-class family where there was no mention of the gospel of Jesus Christ. In spite of this, I had a very good childhood, but always wanted to be the center of attention. When I got to high school, I became the center of attention by drinking and partying instead of going to school.In tenth grade, I met Travis who gave me the attention I wanted, and in twelfth grade, age 17, I became pregnant. Travis' parents and mine were in agreement for us to go ahead and get married. That was just what we wanted! I graduated from high school with a home tutor, but was unable to attend the graduation ceremony because I gave birth to a son, Michael, on June 4, 1972.
			<br /><br />Travis and I always had the "best" parties. All our friends would come over every weekend. But one weekend in February 1973 was different because Steve and Cathy brought some pills called "Speed" with them. Everyone took them except me because I remembered my parents telling me that I would die if I ever took drugs. However, three weekends later, my best friend, Marylou, came over. I noticed that she and my husband were happy on Speed and they didn't die. So I asked for some. It made me so bold that I could hold a conversation with anyone. It was such a false sense of reality, but I didn't realize it at that time.
			<br /><br />In July of 1975, my husband quit and I said to myself, "Well, I'm not going to quit. I like this too much." When Travis went on a business trip to New Jersey, I met a man named Vince who shot drugs, and I let him turn me on to heroin. Well, I really liked heroin more than Speed because, once again, it gave me a false sense of being at peace with myself. I left my son, Michael, with a girlfriend, and took off with Vince to live a drug addict's life. In August 1976, Travis divorced me and received custody of Michael. Then I got on methadone and this enabled me to get a free "high" and be able to take care of my two boys.
			<br /><br />At that time, Vince and I sold cocaine and pot. We had a $150,000 house, a mobile home, four cars, and we travelled anywhere that we wanted. Vince and I had to move a lot because people noticed how young we were to have all those nice things. We didn't want them to realize that we didn't even work, so we moved at least two to three times a year. June 6, 1980, Vince and I were legally married. I remembered telling myself, "Carol, you have it all - a husband, two boys, a great marriage, and all the drugs you want."
			<br /><br />One day in April 1982, Vince came home to break the news to me that he was leaving me for another woman. I took everything on the dresser and threw it at him. I was crying so hard, I just couldn't believe that he would leave me, that it was all over. I thought of a good idea! If I could have another child by Vince, I would keep him. Of course, it didn't work, but on July 3, 1983, I gave birth to Keara who was addicted to methadone.
			<br /><br />After six weeks, I was able to bring her home. I was really depressed now, so I drowned my sorrows with vodka. I stayed drunk a lot and I was unable to take care of my boys, Vince, Jr. and Nicholas. I left them with their dad, but somehow I managed to take care of Keara. I hated everyone and I was mad at the world for the hurt and pain that I was going through. I took methadone, shot heroin, and drank vodka. I started prostituting all day so that I could be high on alcohol and drugs all night. I don't even remember half the time where my daughter was.
			
			<br /><br />One day in November of 1986, a man pulled up to the curb beside me and I got in. This night was very different from all others because he said, "I'm happily married." Right away I thought to myself, "Well, what in the world are you doing picking me up?" He saw my puzzled look and said, "Don't worry! I want to tell you about the Lord Jesus Christ who came to save sinners like you." I said, "Oh! yea? Who is He?" He proceeded to tell me for about two hours at least, but because I started needing a drink, I told him that I had to go. So he gave me $20 and told me to please go in off the street. For some reason, I did! I remembered all that night how different this man was from all other people I had ever met.
			<br /><br /><br />This man's name was Ralph Johnson. Ralph came back to look me up and talk with me further about the Lord. I asked to meet his wife, so one day he found me and had his wife and daughter, Ruth, with him. His wife, Isabel, was glad to meet me and my daughter Keara. I used my street name - June Christie - until I was sure that they were not undercover police officers.
			<br /><br /><br />Ralph and Isabel made many visits and tried faithfully to tell me how I could have a new life if I would only let the Saviour come into my heart. As we got better acquainted, I felt that I could trust them and would call them to help me many times. When I got arrested for prostitution, I called and asked Ralph if he would take off work and go with me to court. He did. The next time I had to go to court, I was sentenced to 30 days in jail. The Johnsons were left with Keara, my 2-year old daughter. When I was released, instead of coming to get my daughter, I spent an entire weekend for myself to enjoy getting "high" again after the month's detox.
			<br /><br /><br />I moved several times while the Johnsons were trying to befriend me. They felt sorry for both Keara and me and finally convinced me to come out to their house in Beltsville, MD. I liked the living arrangement and my daughter made a lot of progress with the stable environment and love that was shown to us. However, in spite of all the Johnsons were doing for me, my addiction again got the best of me and I left their house with my daughter.
			
			<br /><br />One day, I called Isabel in mid-morning and asked her if she would take me out to Montgomery General Hospital for their 28-day detox program. I wanted desperately to get off vodka. Well, I didn't make it out to that hospital because I passed out in her car. She stopped at a fire station and asked for help. They revived me after awhile and then took me by ambulance to the nearest hospital.
			<br /><br /><br />When I came to, I didn't know the plans, but I just wanted out. I got out of the restraints and left the hospital. When the Johnsons arrived to take me home, they were told that I had run off. Remembering from the morning that Keara was my daughter, the head nurse called and turned her in to Social Services.
			<br /><br /><br />The Johnsons were allowed to keep Keara until Social Services found an available foster parent home for her. When the court date arrived, I was glaring daggers at the Johnsons who had brought Keara to the court Custody Hearing. Only after presenting me with a photograph of my daughter was I broken and the tension lessened. My husband and his mother came, and he was granted custody of Keara, while I tried every kind of detox program.
			<br /><br />I occasionally cleaned up my life - only to be dragged back downtown into the alleys with my drinking buddies again. There was no contact with the Johnsons for approximately four years. From that time on until 1989, I was in and out of detox programs and hospitals, trying to get set free from my addictions. Nothing worked. I had so much hate, anger, and jealousy.
			
			<br /><br />On July 15, 1989, a man named Frank Vaughan noticed that I was homeless. That wasn't hard to tell since I hadn't had a bath for over a month and just had on a dress with no underclothing or shoes. He asked me if I would like to come to his apartment where I could get a shower, something to eat, and a good night's sleep on his couch. This sounded so good to me because I had been sleeping in the back seat of an abandoned car in an alley of DC, reeking with alcohol.
			<br /><br />The next morning, this man Frank told me about a Man who loved me and wanted very much to help me. He could take away my addiction. Well, nobody else had been able to help me up to that time. I knew what was coming: "The Man is the Lord Jesus Christ."
			<br /><br />I had hit bottom. I was desperate for help, the kind of help that only He could give. I started asking Frank all kinds of questions about Jesus, and he always answered them, using verses from the Bible. I couldn't understand why Frank put up with me or even let me stay in his own apartment. He opened it up to me and said that it was mine, too. I couldn't believe that Frank liked me for who I was, but Frank's words were: "It's Jesus who loves you."
			<br /><br />I then longed for this Jesus. I wanted this Man, and that night I heard the gospel like I had never heard it before. It was like the cotton had fallen out of my ears and I could hear. I remember saying to myself, "Why didn't anyone else tell me about Jesus like Frank did." Little did I know that it was the work of the Holy Spirit. I was ready to receive Christ into my heart. It was September 15, 1990, when I heard a preacher on TV quote Revelation 3:20, "Behold I stand at the door and knock. If any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come in and sup with him and he with me." That is when I realized that I needed to let the Lord Jesus into my heart. He was standing at my heart's door knocking and I let Him in. I remember crying and repenting of my sins, being extremely sorry for all that I had done against Him, and asking Him to come into my life. I remember a great weight taken off my shoulders. I started attending church services with Frank and was baptized October 28, 1990.
			<br /><br /><br />Then in March 1991, I fell. I started drinking again. I remember feeling horrible for drinking, but I couldn't seem to stop. Finally, on July 21, 1991, I laid on Frank's couch and told the Lord, "Lord, I have had it. I'm so tired of this drinking. As of right now, I give You my whole heart, my whole mind, my whole soul, my whole body. You do with it as You please. It's all Yours, Lord."
			<br /><br />I suddenly noticed that the pain I had in my stomach from drinking was all gone. As the day went on, I had no more desire or thoughts about drinking. I, all of a sudden, realized that the anger, the hurt, and the pain that I carried around was all gone. Then I remember running up to Frank and saying, "Praise the Lord. It's all over. It's all gone. I've been set free." Praise the Lord Jesus Christ! I have been totally set free.
			<br /><br />Frank continued to teach me the Scriptures and read from his bed where he lay, stricken with lung cancer. Then I started reading to him and I learned a lot. Frank went home to be with the Lord on January 8, 1992.
			<br /><br />I called the Johnsons that evening, and we were reunited. They again made room for me in their home. I took a course at the Red Cross and received a Certificate for Home Health Care. Soon after, I was hired to help a lady who had a stroke. I was able to get Keara back, first of all for weekends and then all summer. She has now entered our neighborhood school. My two sons have made visits to our home with the Johnsons. I began going to the chapel where the Johnsons attend and have been received into fellowship with the believers there.
			<br /><br />I'll never forget July 21, 1991, when the Lord Jesus Christ set me free! I have all new thoughts, I have a heart that loves all people, and I love to tell people about the Lord. I hope my testimony will be used to the glory of God and to help others to know that the answer lies only in the Lord Jesus Christ, the Friend of sinners like me.
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="erics-secret">
		<title>Eric's Secret</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/CarSnow-cropped.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Eric Cameron</strong>
			It had been snowing for some time in London, Ontario. Nature's white blanket had been pulled across the landscape once more and Eric Cameron thought it would be a good day to stay inside. It had not been long since doctors had diagnosed him as a victim of ALS - amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Most folk called it simply Lou Gehrig's disease after the famous baseball player who died from it. In 1984, Eric had been given two years to live. Already he needed two canes to assist him as the motor nerve cells in his spinal cord began to succumb to the disease. He knew the prognosis. Five in every one hundred thousand have it. The cause is unknown. There is no cure. The disease is fatal.
			<br /><br /><br />But Eric knew something else. At the age of twelve, on a Sunday night in his home town in Scotland, he lay in bed thinking about his eternal destiny. Then, calling to his father, he spelled out, letter by letter, "I w-a-n-t t-o b-e s-a-v-e-d." For almost forty years he had walked with the Lord since that night. When he could no longer walk, he would sit with the Lord, then lie down with Him. Whatever the doctors said his future would hold, he knew who was holding him.
			<br /><br /><br />Suddenly Eric's attention was arrested by the sight of a neighbor woman whose car had become firmly lodged in a snow bank. Pulling himself up with the liberal use of his canes, he bundled himself against the cold and headed outdoors to help. If he propped himself against the bumper and used his upper body strength &hellip; There! The car broke free of the drift. There were more drifts, however, out to the road. Eric offered to plow the driveway as well.
			<br /><br />Unknown to the two involved in this little winter drama, another neighbor was watching from his window. Stuart Underhill was deeply impressed by this simple act of Christian kindness, especially by someone with an obvious handicap.
			<br /><br />There the story might have ended but for two factors. Stuart's brother Marvin, a believer in Christ, had prayed for years for his brother's conversion. And Helen, Eric's wife, shortly thereafter visited the Underhills with some baked goods. When Stuart mentioned to her the impression it had made on him, Helen offered to bring Mr. Jim Boswell, a local evangelist, for a visit. The Underhills agreed.
			
			<br /><br />After several visits by Mr. Boswell, the Underhills put their trust in the Saviour. Not long after, Mrs. Underhill passed away.
			<br /><br /><br />Eric had manifested his love for the Lord in the bright days of his youth. He had moved to Canada with his parents after World War II. Settling in Hamilton, Ontario, he had joined his father in the orthodontic business, making orthopedic braces and other aids for handicapped people, particularly children. Eventually he expanded the business to London because of the children's hospital there. His parents joined him in the early 1980's where, he said, "I'll look after you for the last part of your lives, as you looked after me for the first part of mine." But it was not to be.
			<br /><br /><br />In those sunshine years Eric is remembered for his robust health, his radiant countenance, his rich baritone voice and his willingness to help. Then came the doctor's report.
			<br /><br /><br />The medical journals describe the course of the disease. They leave no doubt as to its conclusion. The victims gradually lose strength and muscle control in their extremities. Soon they are unable to walk, then to stand. The weakness moves toward their upper body until their arms hang limply by their sides. In the final stages, the lungs no longer function and the victim dies from suffocation. Is God's grace enough for that?
			
			<br /><br />In 1986, Eric's doctors estimated that he had less than six months to live. But God had more than six months' work for him to do. Eric left for the land where redeemed souls walk and run and never tire on July 19, 1990.
			<br /><br /><br />Did the darkness of the advancing disease envelope Eric Cameron's soul? Without exception the doctors and nurses who treated him passed comment on his courage, peace and happy attitude. The anger that they saw so frequently in other patients was completely absent in Eric. He was not slow to tell you his secret.
			<br /><br /><br />On one of his frequent hospital stays, a psychiatrist suffering from Parkinson's became a close friend of Eric's who shared the Gospel with him. The contact extended beyond the hospital through phone calls, letters and tapes. Recent letters indicate that the man has trusted the Saviour.
			<br /><br /><br />Another ALS sufferer was reached when Eric learned that the man, an M.D., was in need of a motorized wheelchair. Eric gave him the one he was no longer able to use himself. The doctor and his wife were frightened and in great distress. They came to visit the Camerons several times afterward. Eventually Eric sent him a tape with a Gospel message, saying he felt constrained to do it, though it might cause an end to their friendship. After listening to it, however, the man said he longed to "have what Eric had." When his wife called to tell them of his passing, she said, "Tom was completely at peace and ready to go."
			<br /><br /><br />A flood of tributes to Eric's life and testimony have come to the family from fellow patients, medical personnel, neighbors and friends. His wife Helen adds: "He was granted the courage and ability to speak to so many that his life would never have touched if he had not been ill."
			<br /><br /><br />There are many philosophies and religions that try to tell you how to live. Only the Gospel can show you how to die. The simple stone that marks Eric Cameron's grave has engraved on it his secret: "To you who believe He (Jesus Christ) is precious."
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="can-a-god-of-love-command-destruction-on-people">
		<title>Can a God of love command destruction on people</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/AFathersLove.jpg" />
			Everyone who engages in conversations about God and the Bible will bump into this question sooner or later: "If God is a God of love, how could He command the slaughter of men, women and children in the Old Testament - for example, such passages as Deuteronomy 20:17?"
			<br /><br /><br />A cursury reading of the Old and New Testaments may give the impression that the God of the OT and the Jesus of the NT are entirely different. One seems to be full of vengeance and ready to judge, while the other is full of love and ready to forgive. Obviously, this cannot be the case since the Lord Jesus is the full revelation of the Father.
			<br /><br />Notice the following key points:
			<br /><br />1. The testimony of the OT is that God is "ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and forsookest them not" (Neh 9:17). See also Ps 103:8; 145:8; Joel 2:13; and Jonah 4:2. This longsuffering was not only to Israel but also toward Gentile nations. The last verse refers to the sparing of Ninevah, and we know the Lord withheld judgment on one Canaanite nation "for the iniquity of the Amorites [was] not yet full" (Gen 15:16). This judgment prophesied in the days of Abram was withheld for almost 1,000 years until the days of King Saul.
			<br /><br />2. The testimony of the NT is that judgment is also surely coming in this age as well: "the Lord Jesus shall be revealed from heaven with his mighty angels, in flaming fire taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ" (2 Thess 1:7-8).
			<br /><br />3. God has used one nation to bring judgment on another. The judgment of the Canaanites coincided with the exodus of the Israelites, just as the rise of the Assyrians coincided with God's judgment on the Israelites. God is fair, and in the end will be seen to have been just in all His dealings.
			<br /><br />4. God has the right to judge His creatures. A key question is asked in Romans 3:5,<br />"Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance?" Here is the crux of the matter. If there is to be justice in the universe, it cannot be left to the law courts of men. Even those who seek to be just often find true justice beyond them. How can human law serve justice when someone has murdered a child? The child cannot receive justice at the hands of men.
			<br /><br />Only the Lord Jesus, into whose hands have been given all judgment (Jn 5:22; Acts 17:31) will be able to set things right in the world.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-nail-pierced-hand">
		<title>The Nail-Pierced Hand</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/BarbedWireWall.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Alfred Wiener</strong>
			I was born, the son of Jewish parents, in the city of Frankfurt on Main, in southwest Germany. My father, a successful insurance representative, was a loyal subject of the ruling house of the Hohenzollern and felt that he was a good German. My mother was an accomplished pianist. I was brought up in an atmosphere of culture, which actually took the place of religion. Our religious training was confined to two hours a week when a fine rabbinical teacher came to the school to give us basic training in Judaism. We were taught selected stories of the Old Testament, called the Tanaach, and some Scripture portions.
			<br /><br />Every year on Good Friday I went to the concert hall to listen to one of the master works of music, "The Passion of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, according to St. Matthew," by Bach. The best musicians took part. Many Jewish choir members sang in this oratorio, seemingly unconcerned as to its meaning.
			<br /><br />When I was about 14, having arrived home from this oratorio, I began to think about Jesus. I read Matthew 26 and 27. Gradually the Person of Jesus of Nazareth came into focus. "This, indeed, was a great man, this man Jesus," I argued in myself, "a great example, a great teacher, a great prophet. Too bad that He had to die the death of a martyr; this could have been avoided." That He, the Son of God, had come down from heaven to take my place in the divine judgment of my sin of course did not enter my mind.
			<br /><br />But where was I to turn? Was there any answer at all? Was there any meaning in life? Was there a God? The great question came to my mind "Where will I go after death? I thought the philosophers would have the answer. Finally I came, in one of Plato's Dialogues, to the utterance of Socrates where he says: "I know that I know nothing." This was a great blow for me. I would have to go through many more testings and trials before, in deepest night and desperation, the answer to all these questions would come from above.
			<br /><br />Hitler appeared on the scene in 1923. By 1928, the National Socialist Party returned as the strongest party of the House. Eventually the old president, Marshall von Hindenburg, entrusted Hitler with the government of Germany. This happened on January 30, 1933.
			<br /><br />Hitler proceeded with the segregation of the Jewish citizens of Germany, called the "cold persecution." The so-called "citizenship law" of the German nation decreed that only those were considered German citizens who had no "Jewish blood" in their veins.
			<br /><br />The next step was "Name Legislation." The Jewish men had to add the name "Israel," and the Jewish women the name "Sarah." If Hitler had known their meanings, he would have chosen other names of shame. "Israel" means prince with God, and "Sarah," princess.
			
			<br /><br />The "cold persecution" of the Jews came to an end in November of 1938. In revenge for the shooting in Paris of Legation Secretary Walter Vom Rath by a young Jew named Greenspan, all the synagogues were set on fire. No fire department was permitted to interfere. Furthermore every Jewish man was to be rounded up and taken to concentration camps.
			<br /><br />On November 10, I saw the Westend Synagogue in Frankfurt, a beautiful building, go up in flames. Still not aware of what was in store, I went to my office. The foreman saw me come in and shouted, "Mr. Wiener, you are mad? Don't you know that the Gestapo will be here shortly to take you away?"
			<br /><br />Going back through the city, I saw the smashing of the windows of the Jewish stores and the looting. Arriving at home, I was told that my cousin and my second youngest brother had already been picked up from the street when they went out in the morning.
			<br /><br />At noon on November 12, the door bell rang. There stood two storm troopers and a policeman. They left me about 15 minutes to collect my most necessary belongings. I went quickly into the attic room where I had spent so many times of study and searching for truth. I had a little candle which I always lit before I said my prayers. I kindled it quickly, knelt down, and committed myself into the hand of God. At that crucial moment, I was convinced in my soul that Jesus was the Messiah of Israel, and that He had come to bring redemption and new life to His ancient people, but I had not yet surrendered to Him. Yet, in that moment of fatal danger, I did not know where to go except to Him!
			<br /><br />We were taken to the great concert hall of Frankfurt, the same hall where in former days I had listened to "Matthew's Passion" and the "Messiah" by Handel. But that day, November 12, 1938, there was no music. Black uniformed guards brought in Jewish men from all the surrounding districts. On November 12, they arrested about 2,000 Jewish men.
			<br /><br />At midnight, after they took away our meager belongings, we were taken to the railway station. The populace at the station received us with what sounded like animal noises. Quite a few shouted: "Concentration camp for you dirty Jews!" The guards chased us into the train, and we were on our way.
			<br /><br />The morning of November 13 dawned. The train stopped at Weimar, the famous city of high culture, for many years the residence of the world famous poet, playwright and philosopher, Johann Wolfgang von Goethe. Trucks were ready at the station to ship us to the camp about 20 miles north of Weimar. Anyone not able to climb up fast enough was pitilessly beaten. Many broke their arms and legs. It was Sunday morning. Up we went, in beautiful sunshine, autumn leaves in full color - to the gate of hell.
			
			<br /><br />Buchenwald, as with all the camps, was surrounded by barbed wire charged with high voltage. Anyone who touched it was electrocuted immediately. Watchtowers at regular intervals were manned by the guards. They were, as Hitler termed it, "trained for the special duties of the concentration camps." We learned very soon what this meant.
			<br /><br />At the time I was captured, I was suffering with an open cyst on the upper right jaw. My nerves were at the brink of exhaustion. A deep depression had taken hold of me, which, if aggravated much more, could easily have deteriorated into a mental disturbance which would have had fatal consequences.
			<br /><br />Then came another announcement: "No water; nothing to drink for newcomers for three days!" Three days without anything to drink brings a person to utter exhaustion. At night they gave us the first "meal," a salty soup. Of course this only increased our thirst.
			<br /><br />It was about ten o'clock when they ordered us into the barrack. Inside were just boards, five stories high. Of course, there was no stairway. Anyone who had to climb higher than the boards next to the floor had to climb up in a very cumbersome way. There were scarcely any water pipes laid and no latrines. I will not go into all the details. It was like descending into the abyss. What hope could we possibly have?
			<br /><br />During that first night of terror we finally fell exhausted on the planks, dying of thirst, without blankets in the cold air of November; we hoped that now we would be able to sleep. It was dark, terribly dark.
			<br /><br />I had searched for truth. Through many avenues of error, I had come to recognize the main issue of our existence as Jews - that the Jews were taken out from among the nations in order to bring the Saviour into this world. Through the prophets, warning after warning was given to God's earthly people not to miss this turning point of the ages. But, "He came unto His own, and His own received Him not"!
			<br /><br />Oh, tragedy of our beloved Jewish people! God, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, cannot let them go. He told them that unto them "a child [would be] born," unto them "a Son [would be] given," and that His name would be called "Wonderful, Counsellor, the mighty God, the everlasting Father, the Prince of Peace" (Isa. 9:6); that He, the Messiah, would be their sinbearer, that by "His stripes" they would be "healed" (Isa. 53:5). They were told of this wonderful plan of redemption over and over again; but they did not open the door when the great hour of His appearing arrived.
			<br /><br />I came to Jesus by night, like Nicodemus. I found, by comparing Old and New Testaments, that all the prophecies concerning the Messiah fitted perfectly on Jesus of Nazareth. I found something else. Our rabbis told us that man can come into the presence of God by keeping the law and doing "mizvahs" (good deeds) to our fellow men. But God says throughout the Old Testament: "For the life of the flesh is in the blood: and I have given it to you upon the altar to make an atonement for your souls: for it is the blood that maketh an atonement for the soul" (Lev. 17:11).
			<br /><br />The question came to me, "Who is right, God or the rabbis?" When I came to Buchenwald, there was no doubt in my mind that God was right. He says in Malachi 3:6: "I am the Lord, I change not; therefore ye sons of Jacob are not consumed." If He does not change, then His plan of salvation has not changed. Then His means of salvation cannot change, either! I asked: "Where is the blood today? Where is the sacrifice? Where is the altar? It must be somewhere."
			
			<br /><br />During that first night in Buchenwald, the most awful things happened. Minutes after the lights had been switched out, the doors were opened and the guards came in like hyenas, taking out at random Jewish men - honorable men! They ordered them out into the yard and then the "manhunt" began. We heard, first muffled, then louder, the orders: "Run, you Jews! Dirty Jews, run! Run faster!" The guards had dogs with them, snarling German shepherds. If these unhappy Jewish men could not run fast enough, they were caught by the dogs and torn to pieces, or stabbed by the guards who had butcher knives in their hands. Those who were able to run fast enough were chased across the yard of the camp right into the electric wire where they died instantly.
			<br /><br />The screaming of those who met their end in this way was so frightening that, during this first night, I came very near to losing my mind. Many went mad.
			<br /><br />Here I was, naked before God. There was no escape any more. I knew that I was coming fast to the brink of death. What if I should pass into eternity and should hear the terrible words: "Too late!"? Too late to come the right way! Now I was near the breaking point - no hope any more, no way out, hopelessly fenced in, drawn toward the abyss of an eternity of horror by powerful invisible hands.
			<br /><br />But that hellish taskmaster, Roedl, the commander of Buchenwald, left us no time for even thinking. "Juden auf den Hof!" We dragged ourselves outside. We had to stand, stand, stand. An icy wind made my exhausted frame shiver feverishly. I felt that the end had come. Not only the end of my physical existence, but something much worse, an end - not life, but not death either - in which the soul becomes irreparable, hopelessly damaged, eternally fixed - no sleep at all, but stagnant, staring, timeless wakefulness under unspeakable tortures.
			<br /><br />The next day, we were insulted by the commander through the loudspeaker with all the insults which have been hurled against the Jews for centuries. "You Jewish swine, you have stolen all the money. You tried to bring the German people under your dirty rule. You have tried to seize control of all German life. But the Fuehrer is our deliverer from you pests! We will exterminate you like vermin. This is our task. Invincible will be our crusade against you Unterasse (inferior race). There will be a holy war against you for the purpose of delivering the world from you!"
			<br /><br />Perhaps there are some incredulous readers who might think that we have dreamt up these stories of terror. I can assure you that there is nothing whatsoever exaggerated. Words cannot possibly describe the inferno of a Hitler camp.
			<br /><br />But now listen to what happened to me in that most crucial, most helpless moment in Buchenwald, November 14 and 15, 1938.
			<br /><br />Again the guards came in. Again they forced Jewish men out into the yard. Suddenly, a horrible sight unfolded before my eyes. I saw my mother dying in the concentration camp. I heard voices accusing me that I had murdered my mother because I was thinking only of myself and had not acted in time to rescue her. The horrors to which I had been exposed were nothing compared to this! It cut to my heart. The accusing voices grew stronger. "You know," someone said, "he refused to register her in time at the American Consulate. He saved his own skin, but did not care for his mother. He has deserved death!"
			<br /><br />In reality, my mother was still living in Frankfurt. It was four years later that she and my sisters were deported to Terezin where she died in 1944.

			<br /><br />And then, while I was sinking still deeper into what natural reason would have called a delirious condition, or a delusion, but which was exceedingly real to me, the picture changed again. I stood, as it were, at the ramp of the orchestra pit of our opera house in Frankfurt, and I saw how, from all sides, books, books, my books, which I cherished so much, and my manuscripts, were thrown by invisible hands into this orchestra pit. A fire was kindled, and my books and papers were burnt. Nothing remained. I was robbed of all my proud achievements.
			<br /><br />Then all these pictures vanished. A terrific abyss opened up. I saw hands reaching out after me, ready to pull me down into an eternity of horror and perdition. I wanted to cry out, but I could not. I was paralyzed. Although I was, as far as this life is concerned, surrounded by the shrieking of those outside our barrack being chased to their death, I did not hear anything anymore from the sounds without. No noises seemed to penetrate this horrid torment.
			<br /><br />Then came a hand from above, one hand from above against many hands from beneath! And in that one hand was the print of a nail.
			<br /><br />At this moment, a voice was given to me to cry, and I cried to Him in the midst of this horrible camp: "Lord Jesus Christ, my Saviour, my Redeemer, I die. But Thou, Thou alone art able to help me! Thou alone art able to rescue me from the wrath of God! I am a sinner, a horrible, helpless sinner. But Thou camest down from heaven to rescue me, Thy lost child! Help me, Lord Jesus! I surrender all to Thee." And crying to Him who alone is able to save to the uttermost, I lost consciousness.
			<br /><br />Though I know that the Holy Spirit has to reprove the resistant derelict of sin and righteousness and judgment, I am thoroughly convinced, after this experience, that free will was never taken away from man. It was my privilege to have a real hour of decision and to receive the divine confirmation of the words of the Lord spoken to His people in Deuteronomy 30:15, "See, I have set before thee this day life and good, and death and evil" - mighty words corroborated by God Himself through Jeremiah (21:8).
			<br /><br />When I lost consciousness, I was, humanly speaking, doomed to death. Anyone who did, or who went out of his mind, was thrown into the laundry kitchen by the guards and left there to die. How easily I could have been among them! But I awoke in the camp "hospital," a barrack with about sixty beds. It had to be sufficient for ten thousand men. To get there was next to impossible. To survive there was a greater miracle.
			<br /><br />I stayed a few more days in the camp hospital. Then I was released back to the barracks. This was another miracle, but I did not at the time understand just from what I had been delivered. Much later, I read in Dr. Eugen Kogon's hair-raising documentary report, The Theory and Practice of Hell, that I had been miraculously delivered from a place from which scarcely anyone ever emerged alive.
			<br /><br />Then I heard how I was rescued. The supervisor of our block, a Jewish gentleman from Breslau, had watched over me, and had finally got me to the hospital. This man told me he protected me because I was "in a delirious condition," as he termed it, always crying, "Christ! Christ!" He could not understand how I, a Jew, could ring out this name. He attributed it to my allegedly "delirious" condition.
			
			<br /><br />Two weeks after we had been taken to Buchenwald, in the wake of this first wave of persecution, the releases from the camp started. At that time, about three years before the so-called final solution (complete extermination of the Jews) the Nazis still permitted emigration from Germany under two conditions: that a man was a veteran of the First World War, and/or a document of emigration was provided for the prisoner by relatives or friends in another country. Both these conditions were met in my case. I had been in France with the German army in 1918, and an old friend of my parents, a prominent Jewish man in New York, provided an affidavit for me to emigrate to the United States as soon as my quota number, which was very high, would be called up.
			<br /><br />From December 1 on, every day names were called through the loudspeaker - men who were ready for release. Everyone in the camp strained to hear his name. On December 13, 1938, I heard my name called. This was the third miracle.
			<br /><br />We had to sign a document that we had not suffered any bodily harm in the concentration camp, a farce because many who were released had suffered irreparable physical and mental damage.
			<br /><br />Finally, we stood at the gate, about sixty Jewish men. Grim had been my reception to Buchenwald, but what incomprehensible blessedness that I was privileged to experience the grace of God there. "For I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, saying unto thee, Fear not, thou worm Jacob, and ye men of Israel; I will help thee, saith the Lord, and thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel" (Isa. 41:13-14)! If we clasp our hand - empty of anything we can do - into His nail-pierced hand which reaches out from heaven to rescue us, we are washed in the precious blood of His eternal atonement.
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="what-the-cannibal-was-hungry-for">
		<title>What the Cannibal Was Hungry For</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/AfricanSpearShield.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Bishop Leigh</strong>
			In a fit of violent temper, I left home when I was nineteen and joined the crew of a freighter which was sailing for India. My life became more and more sinful until I lost all concern for anything of true worth. It seemed that my wish that I would some day travel so far from home that I would never again hear the name of Jesus was realized. I never heard the name of Jesus except in swearing, and I thought myself glad.
			<br /><br /><br />In the spring of my twenty-first year, we sailed to South Africa for ore. There I met two men, Peters and Edwards, who were planning a safari for ivory into the jungles of Rhodesia. Hearing their plans fired me with a desire to go along with them. I had a difficult time persuading them to let me join them, for I knew nothing of jungle life. However they finally agreed; I deserted my job and slipped away with the safari.
			<br /><br /><br />After long, difficult months of jungle travel, we found ourselves in the Zambezi region. An encounter with an enraged elephant herd and jungle diseases had claimed the lives of several of our porters. Several others deserted the safari. Space does not permit telling of how Peters was killed by a lion, and Edwards died with a raging fever. The porters refused to carry on, and I was left alone in the jungle. Can you imagine my despair?
			<br />For several days, I wandered southward, knowing that my only hope was to reach the Zambezi River and follow it out of the jungle. After three days of wandering alone, I began to feel I was being watched. For weeks we had seen no natives, but I was now conscious that human eyes were on me.
			<br /><br /><br />It was no figment of my imagination. Before I reached the Zambezi, I was captured by ten natives, armed with spears. They led me to a village, and placed me in a straw hut. I knew what my fate was, for this was a fierce tribe, well known for their cannibalism. I knew they would keep me until a day when all the tribes would gather for an orgy of feasting. Edwards and Peters had told me of the character of the peoples in this region. I grimly awaited my fate.
			<br /><br /><br />A bowl of plantains was shoved through the door to me twice daily and that was all my fare. For two days I saw no one and remained in my dark, guarded hut. Then an escort of several natives came to me. I found out later that this was Easter Sunday. It had been the most gruesome Easter I had ever experienced. My life hung by a thread.
			<br /><br /><br />I was taken to the hut of the chief, who sat on a bench with his rod of authority in his hand. Everything was quiet as he scrutinized me with great care. In aching silence, I stood before this fierce-looking chief for what seemed an eternity. I held my head up and determined to die with courage. Then the tribal chief gestured with his hand and spoke. I can't imitate his words and shall not try, but I understood him as he asked, "You know Jesus?"
			<br /><br /><br />Never in my life did I hear a name so sweet! I fell right down on the floor of that dirty hut and wept like a baby. This was the name I had been running from. I had run this far and could run no further. I cried to the Lord for forgiveness and yielded my life to Him for His service. I remembered the quotation of Scripture: "Whither shall I go from Thy Spirit? or whither shall I flee from Thy presence? &hellip; If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea; even there shall Thy hand lead me, and Thy right hand shall hold me." I had learned the verse at home many years, many miles before. Lying on that hut floor, I acknowledged to God it was a true promise. That Easter became an Easter indeed to me.
			<br /><br /><br />I stayed with these natives more than half a year, during which time I taught them much about Jesus. It was David Livingstone who had first taught them about the Lord, but they were still clinging to many primitive superstitions. How thankful I was for the background of Christian knowledge my parents had given me. I was eager to return to my parents whose hearts I had deliberately tried to break. I feared that they might die before they knew of my conversion. God was merciful, however, and they were both living when I reached England ten months after the time of my conversion. Each Easter became an occasion of double rejoicing in our home. "I am He that liveth, and was dead" (Rev. 1:18), said the Lord Jesus. I am living proof He can do it in your life too.
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="carl-greer-gets-life">
		<title>Carl Greer Gets Life</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/GetsLife.jpg" />
			<strong class="no-top-margin">by Carl Greer</strong>
			I was born in Gulfport, Mississippi, on July 6, 1952, but lived most of my life in southeast Louisiana. I grew up in a religious family that talked about God and prayed often. At a young age, I was baptized into a denominational church that my parents attended for a short time. The pastor, a friend of the family, was accused of drinking on a fishing trip with some of the elders, was dismissed shortly thereafter, and my parents left the church. My mother and father were both alcoholic for as long as I can remember, but they did try the best they knew to be good parents and provide a good home. I can remember believing there was a God, but never gave it much thought past that, and neither I nor any of my family knew Him personally at that time.
			<br /><br /><br />At the age of 13, I began drinking. At 19, I smoked my first "joint." Anyone who says marijuana doesn't lead to stronger drugs just hasn't smoked it long enough. As time passed, I began mixing drugs and alcohol, and, by the time I was 33, my life was totally out of control. One night, in a drug-induced vision so clear I really thought it was happening, I saw myself putting a pistol in my mouth and pulling the trigger. In desperation and fear for my life, I entered a drug and alcohol detoxification program.
			<br />Shortly after being admitted, I began to see my whole life pass before me. The waste, the emptiness, the unhappiness! All the years spent going nowhere! I realized there was something missing in my life &hellip; an emptiness that I could not seem to fill with anything the world, drugs, alcohol or sex had to offer. I started reading the Bible, looking for answers &hellip; something to fill the emptiness. With the guidance of the Holy Spirit, I was led to realize that what I was looking for was not a "what" at all, but a "Who" &hellip; the Lord Jesus! God's Spirit drove home such verses as Isaiah 1:18-20, "Come now, and let us reason together, saith the Lord: though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool. If ye be willing and obedient, ye shall eat the good of the land. But if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the sword; for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it." I realized what I needed to do! So after reading Matthew 6:6 and feeling that the going into a "closet" was somehow involved in the whole process, I climbed into the small military-style wall locker in my hospital room, closed the door, confessed to God that I was a sinner, and accepted Jesus Christ as my Lord and Saviour.
			<br /><br /><br />After thirty days, I was told that for me to go on to the halfway house, I would have to be drug-free for thirty days. At the time, the doctor had prescribed a strong anti-depressant that he said I would need to be on for the rest of my life. This would disqualify me from going on to the halfway house program that I felt I really needed. I knew that "with God, all things are possible," so my first step of faith was to quit taking the anti-depressants. Thirty days later, I went into the halfway house for sixty days, and then on to the three-quarter-way house for another sixty days! By this time, in spite of accepting Christ, I had lost my car, my home, my business, and my family. I was sober, but humanly things didn't look too good. But God is faithful!
			<br /><br />That was five years ago. I still have problems, but now I have peace in my heart and joy in my life, thanks to the Lord Jesus. God has been so good to me. My family and I are back together! I have a good job! I am actively involved in a local assembly with a great group of Christians to gather with! BEST OF ALL, through Christ Jesus I have the gift of God: Life&hellip; Abundant Life&hellip; Life Eternal&hellip; WITH HIM!
			<br />Psalm 34 says: "I sought the Lord, and He heard me, and delivered me from all my fears &hellip; This poor man cried, and the Lord heard him, and saved him out of all his troubles&hellip; Oh, taste and see that the Lord is good; blessed is the man who trusteth in Him." This truly is the story of my life &hellip; IN HIM!
			<br /><br />Originally published in UPLOOK Magazine
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="did-jesus-claim-to-be-god">
		<title>Did Jesus claim to be God?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/jesus-god-or-man.jpg" />
			Christianity stands apart from all the religions of the world. One important reason is that its founder, Jesus Christ, claimed to be fully God. The Buddha did not claim to be God; Moses never said that he was Jehovah; Mohammed did not say he was Allah; and Zoroaster never claimed to be Ahura Mazda. Yet the lowly Carpenter from Nazareth declared that whoever had truly seen Him (Jesus) had seen His Father (John 14:9). Christ said He existed before Abraham: "Your father Abraham rejoiced to see My day: and he saw it, and was glad. Then said the Jews to Him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast Thou seen Abraham? Jesus said to them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was, I am" (John 8:56-58).
			<br /><br />Christ said that He was equal to the Father: "My Father has been working until now, and I have been working." Therefore the Jews sought all the more to kill Him, because He not only broke the Sabbath, but also said that God was His Father, making Himself equal with God" (John 5:17-18).
			<br /><br />Jesus also declared, "As the Father raises the dead and gives life to them, even so the Son gives life to whom He will. For the Father judges no one, but has committed all judgment to the Son" (John 5:21-22). He not only claimed to be God, He proved Himself to be God by raising people from the dead!
			<br /><br />Christ not only said but proved that He could forgive sins. In Mark 2:5-7, we read, "When Jesus saw their faith, He said to the paralytic, "Son, your sins are forgiven you." And some of the scribes were sitting there and reasoning in their hearts, "Why does this Man speak blasphemies like this? Who can forgive sins but God alone?" (Mark 2:5-7). To prove He had the power, Jesus immediately healed the man of his paralysis, giving outward visible evidence of the inward spiritual healing He had also performed in forgiving the man.
			<br /><br />The power to forgive sins against God is something which the Bible clearly teaches only God can do. The Hebrew prophet Isaiah records God as saying, "I, even I, am He that blotteth out thy transgressions for Mine own sake, and will not remember thy sins" (Isaiah 43:25).
			<br /><br />Christ's claims are unmistakable. When He asked the religious authorities why they wanted to stone Him, they replied, "For a good work we stone Thee not; but for blasphemy; and because that Thou, being a man, makest Thyself God" (John 10:33). The Jews understood what He was claiming for Himself even if modern skeptics do not.
			<br /><br />The New Testament teaches that Christ is the Creator of the universe. "All things were made by Him; and without Him was not any thing made that was made" (John 1:3). He continues to hold all things together. "And He is before all things, and by Him all things consist" (Colossians 1:17). Paul says Christ was God manifest in human flesh (1 Timothy 3:16). The apostle John refers to Christ as "the Word" and says "the Word was God" (John 1:1).
			<br /><br />The reality of who Jesus Christ is, is central to Christianity. Between the Person, Jesus Christ, and the religions of the world and their founders, there is a "grand canyon" separating them from one another. Confucianism is a set of teachings; Confucius himself is not central. Islam is supposed to be the revelation of Allah, with Mohammed being only his prophet. Buddhism emphasizes the principles of the Buddha but not Buddha himself. And in the Hindu religion, there is no known historic founder.
			<br /><br />But at the core of Christianity is Christ. He did not just teach about truth, He claimed to be the truth. "Jesus said unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man comes to the Father, except by Me" (John 14:6). Who Jesus Christ is, is the important question for you. Is He the Son of God? Is He the only way to reach God?
			<br /><br />This is why we say that Christianity is not a religion; it is a relationship. You do not become a Christian by merely knowing about Christ and His teachings; you need to know Him personally, "And this is eternal life, that they may know Thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom Thou hast sent" (John 17:3). This knowing comes through reading and responding positively to the central message of the Bible, the Word of God. "You shall know the truth," said Jesus, "and the truth shall make you free."
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="how-could-a-good-god-allow-evil-in-the-world">
		<title>How could a good God allow evil in the world?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/whydoesgodallowevil.jpg" />
			When God made the human race, He did not want toys or machines that could be programmed to do His will. He wanted real people who could really love Him as He would love them. Of course if they could choose to love Him, they could also choose not to love Him. If they could choose to serve Him, they could also choose to rebel against Him. And that is just what happened.
			<br /><br />Evil does not float around unattached, like a big, black cloud over the earth. Evil originates in men's hearts and is committed by human beings like you and me. Sin and death came into the world when Adam rebelled against God in the Garden of Eden. God could have destroyed mankind then, but He chose to redeem us instead. Those who put their faith in Christ are made right with God and will never be condemned because their Substitute took their judgment for them (Romans 8:1-2). But those who exercise their right to choose by rejecting God's free gift of salvation will be judged for their evil deeds (Matthew 13:41-42) since they have never accepted God's forgiveness and eternal life in the Lord Jesus Christ.
			<br /><br />When Jesus first presented Himself to His own people, by and large they rejected His offer: "He came to His own, and His own did not receive Him" (John 1:11). That was their decision. But you also have a decision to make. What will you do with Jesus, the solution to personal evil in your own heart? Of many in the days of the New Testament we read, "But as many as received Him, to them He gave the right to become children of God, to those who believe in His name" (John 1:12).
			<br /><br />God could judge all mankind right now if He chose; He could have done so long ago. Many mock at God's promise to come and judge the earth (2 Peter 3:3-4), but God is not slow in keeping His promise; He is patient as He waits for those very sinners to put their trust in Him (2 Peter 3:9). Some day, however, He will come suddenly and unannounced (2 Peter 3:10) and then the wicked deeds of all unbelievers will be judged.
			<br /><br />But what of the bad things that happen in the world which are not due to the acts of men? What about earthquakes, disease, and famine? The question of suffering is a complex one, and we cannot presume to guess all God's reasons for allowing natural disasters to trouble or even to take the lives of individuals.
			<br /><br />Certain things we do know. First, if God is God, He has the right to take the life of any of His creatures when He chooses. We all must die, because the wages of sin is death. If it is by natural disaster, that is something beyond our control. But being prepared now for whatever comes by receiving eternal life is something we can do.
			<br /><br />Second, we can be sure of the ultimate source of these upheavals in nature. The Bible tells us that these things are the natural consequences of man's sin. All creation was warped when Adam sinned, and throughout history the earth has groaned, waiting for deliverance (Romans 8:22). Creation will not be put right until God has first fully judged the sin that caused its collapse. He has promised to do so, but only He knows the day or the hour at which that judgment will begin (Mark 13:32-33).
			<br /><br />We also know that God is a wise and loving God, not by trying to understand the confusing circumstances of life, but by remembering the Cross of Christ. God made one great declaration of His love when the Lord Jesus gave Himself for us. After that, we should never question His love again. "For God so loved the world that He gave His only begotten Son, that whoever believes in Him should not perish, but have eternal life" (John 3:16).
			<br /><br />We must also understand that many children who are swept away in disasters are swept into a safer and better place than they have ever known. Many little children are rescued from lives of grinding poverty, abuse, and hopelessness by being taken into heaven by a loving Creator.
			<br /><br />If God were to remove all the evil in the world right away, He would have to include you and me. When people realize this, they are a little less strident in their calls for a righteous God to judge the earth. Are you ready for &lsquo;final exams"? It is time to prepare to meet God. Today is the day of salvation.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="what-about-a-good-buddhist-or-hindu">
		<title>What about a good Buddhist or Hindu?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/buddhahindu.jpg" />
			These people are religious and sincere. Will God accept them?
			<br/><br/>Sincerity is absolutely necessary in coming to God. The Bible condemns lying and dishonesty, but often mentions how vital it is to be sincere (note such passages as 1 Corinthians 5:8; 2 Corinthians 1:12; Ephesians 6:24; Philippians 1:10).
			<br /><br />However, it is possible for someone to be sincere, but sincerely wrong. The Bible says there is a way that seems right unto a man, but the end of that way are the ways of death (Proverbs 16:25). A good biblical example of this is Saul of Tarsus, who in all good conscience persecuted the church of God. Was he sincere? Yes. Was he wrong? By his own confession, he was (see 1 Timothy 1:13). We regularly hear of a person foolishly pointing a gun at someone, sincerely believing it to be empty. The gun discharges, and someone is killed. The person who pulled the trigger stands there in shock, saying, "I didn't know it was loaded." That person was 100% sincere in his desire not to harm anyone. But he was sincerely believing something untrue. Safety experts have a saying, "Loaded guns never seem to kill people; it's always empty guns that kill people." A sincere belief in a falsehood can be fatal.
			<br /><br />The apostle Paul warns that practicing religion does not excuse anyone; in fact, it may multiply the religionist's guilt. Pagan religions have deliberately distorted and overthrown truth. They exchanged the truth of God for a lie (Romans 1:25).
			<br /><br />Buddhism rejects the notion of the one true God and Hinduism practices idolatry. God detests idolatry as an "abomination." It is a direct insult to the dignity of God. "Thou shalt have no other gods before Me. Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth: Thou shalt not bow down thyself to them, nor serve them" (Exodus 20:3-5).
			<br /><br />Regardless of sincerity, a religious person who worships the wrong god has no advantage. The doors and the ignition switch to my car will only respond to one set of keys, and that is the way I want it. Likewise there is only one set of keys that unlocks heaven to guilty sinners, and those keys belong to the Lord Jesus Christ. God has not confused us with scores of options for how to get to heaven. Christ said, "I am the way, the truth, and the life. No one comes to the Father except through Me" (John 14:6).
			<br /><br />It is not your belief that provides salvation for you. It is the object of your belief that matters. For example, believing that someone will catch me if I jump from a burning building is only good if someone is actually willing, able, and available to catch me.
			<br /><br />If you don't believe you need a Saviour, any religion will probably do. But if you have discovered something fundamentally wrong within, and you realize you need a Saviour, the list of Saviours offered by the religions of the world is very short - in fact, there is only one. His name is Jesus. No other religion has one (they essentially tell you to save yourself by your own efforts). " &hellip; Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom you crucified, whom God raised from the dead&hellip;Nor is there salvation in any other, for there is no other name under heaven given among men by which we must be saved" (Acts 4:10,12).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="did-jesus-really-rise-from-the-dead">
		<title>Did Jesus really rise from the dead?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/jesus-resurrection.jpg" />
			Paul sums up the importance of the resurrection when he says, "If Christ be not raised, your faith is vain; you are yet in your sins" (1 Corinthians 15:17). Here are six proofs concerning the bodily resurrection of the Lord Jesus:
			<br /><br />1. The Soldiers:<br />The Jews requested that a guard be set at the tomb (Matthew 27:66). Later, the soldiers were told to say they had fallen asleep and the disciples had taken this opportunity to steal the Lord's body (Matthew 28:13). But if they were asleep, how would they know who stole the body? The penalty for a Roman soldier to fall asleep on guard duty was death. No wonder the soldiers wanted protection from the governor (Matthew 28:14) if he heard the story.
			<br /><br />2. The Sealing Stone:<br />Mark 16:4 tells us that the stone that sealed the Lord's crypt was a "great" stone. In fact, the women who came to the grave wondered how they would move it. If the disciples stole the Lord's body, how could they have quietly moved that stone without arousing the guard? And if, as some suggest, Jesus had not really died on the cross, and revived in the cold tomb, there is an even greater problem: how could He, after a severe whipping, several days without food and water, and the horrors of the crucifixion, first escape from the binding graveclothes and then move a stone like that - from the inside of the tomb? And then, weak from severe blood loss and lack of food, He must somehow elude the soldier guards, stagger into town, and then convince His sceptical disciples that He was the resurrection and the life!
			<br /><br />3. The Scripture Record:<br />In a court of law, the corroborating testimony of two witnesses is sufficient to establish a fact. All four Gospel writers attest to the resurrection of Christ, as well as Peter. Thomas, who didn't believe even the witness of his fellow disciples, was won over by the evidence of Christ actually making a personal visit to him, showing Thomas the wounds in His hands and side. In fact, more than 500 saw Him on one occasion; this was evidently no mere figment of someone's overactive imagination.
			<br /><br />Most convincing, perhaps, is the personal testimony of Saul of Tarsus. He had been hired by the Supreme Court in Israel to eradicate the so-called blasphemous cult of Jesus followers. Then one day he became one of them, overwhelmed by the evidence he saw and heard on the Damascus road where he personally met the resurrected Christ. With his name changed to Paul, he wrote almost half of the New Testament, constantly stating the facts of the case: Jesus is alive! "But now Christ is risen from the dead, and has become the firstfruits of those who have fallen asleep" (1 Corinthians 15:20).
			<br /><br />4. The Still Unproduced Body:<br />If the Lord had not risen, the way to quiet those who claimed He did rise was to produce His body. The Romans would not have stolen the body. The cult of Christians became the greatest irritation to their empire, eventually bringing it to its knees. The Jews would not have stolen the body or else they would have carried it through the streets of Jerusalem and pronounced Christianity as dead as their Jesus. Would the disciples have stolen the body, as the soldiers first professed? Why? It was contrary to everything we read about them. First, they were so afraid of the authorities that they cowered behind locked doors. Only a few brave women, driven by the love that overcomes fear, ventured out. Second, they later would declare the resurrection to be a truth worth dying for. Others have died for a lie, but they didn't know it was a lie. These men and women, whose lives showed the highest morality, hardly seem to be a band of charlatans and cheats.
			<br /><br />5. The Suffering of the Disciples:<br />In fact, every one of the Lord's disciples were viciously tortured for his faith in a risen Christ. All but one died a martyr's death, and yet not one denied the resurrection of Christ or admitted it to be a hoax. They continued to declare it to be the greatest event in the annals of human history.
			<br /><br />6. The Scope of the Gospel:<br />It is a historical fact that tens of thousands of people believed in the resurrection at the time of the New Testament's writing, and since then millions have proclaimed their faith in a living Christ. Though sceptics continue to attack the faith, Christ's Church keeps growing. Some would say, "I would have far more faith in the evidence for the resurrection if some non-Christians had examined it in the first century." But isn't that evidence in itself? Everyone who carefully examined the evidence became a Christian!
			<br /><br />Many sceptics since that time, when carefully perusing the case, have also been convinced. C.S. Lewis, Henry Morrison, Lord Lyttleton, Gilbert West, Josh McDowell - the list is impressive. If you are a sceptic, you could add your name to the list, not by being brainwashed into believing some old fiction, but by carefully examining the record in the Bible, especially 1 Corinthians chapter 15. 
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-sound-of-music">
		<title>The Sound of Music</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/FrogCalling_sm.jpg" />
			<em>Is there more to it than meets the ear?</em>
			The arrival and passing of summer in the central plains of North America is marked by characteristic sounds. The song of chorus frogs means the spring rains have awakened eggs laid last year. The distinctive call of the western meadowlark signals the beginning of an annual search for a mate. The heat of summer brings the pulsating buzz of the cicada from the branches above. Late summer is heralded by the noisy, intermittent buzz and clicks of mature grasshoppers and katydids.
			<br /><br />There is purpose in each of these distinguishing calls or sounds: they help male and female of the same species find each other; they signal danger; others are claims of territory or threats before a fight. But can any animal sounds really be called music in the sense that humans understand music?
			<br /><br />In my town, summer is marked by weekly concerts of the city band in a tree-shaded park. The events draw hundreds of listeners of all ages. For an hour, the audience is swept away by the music. Yet, though all hear the same music, each person feels its effect differently. The beauty and power of music are undeniable. Surely music can do all that the limited, rudimentary sounds of frogs, birds, and insects can do: communicate a sense of danger; energize for a fight; even claim territory - think of your national anthem. But it can also move one to tears or rouse the spirit to the pinnacle of joy. It can calm the heart or trigger lost memories. Music is the language of emotion, and there is no true parallel in the animal world.
			<br /><br />But why should this be so? Believers in the philosophy of naturalism have no answer for why humans would spend time and energy to write, perform, and listen to music. After all, such behavior in what they see as the human "animal" has no survival advantage and so makes no evolutionary sense. It is here that the reductionist thinking of those committed to naturalism runs afoul of reality - they respond to music in the same ways as believers in Christ. As human beings, they are haunted by the reality of the beauty and power of the sound of music, even as their naturalism forces them to reject such thoughts as mere illusion created by purposeless chance and natural selection. Meaning is not found in music by reducing the sounds to the mechanics of their production. This is seeing the world wrong side out. Instead, the mechanics is the basis to express meaning and emotion which are part of the image of God within us.1 Just as our own logic and reason reflect God's intellect and consistency and the existence of moral standards reflects God's character, the sound of music touches the remnant of God's image within us as emotion. To appreciate the power of logic, the security of morality, and the emotion of music but reject the ultimate source of these gifts is to embrace only a fading shadow of reality.
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br />1. Josh McDowell, Thomas Williams. In Search Of Certainty. Green Key Books. Holiday, Florida. 2003.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="SETI-in-their-ways">
		<title>SETI in Their Ways</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/SETI_Alien.jpg" />
			The "Ask the Experts" question and answer section in the July 2004 issue of Scientific American fielded a question about the program called SETI, the Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence (p. 120). The question posed was: "What kind of patterns does SETI look for?"
			<br /><br />The answer, given by Peter R. Backus, programs manager at SETI, is a good example of how adherents to the evolutionary faith continue to miss the obvious even when they are looking for it.
			<br /><br />The goal of SETI is to find signs of intelligent life beyond earth by monitoring light and radio waves hitting earth from space and searching them for patterns. Their reasoning is that humans cannot be alone in the universe and for them it is a virtual certainty that life has begun and evolved on other planets, perhaps even to the point of being able to broadcast radio signals. Since only a living, intelligent being can consistently make and broadcast signals that are nonrandom or coded, finding patterns would be the first tangible evidence for the existence of life outside of earth. For SETI followers this would also be proof of their faith that earth is not unique and that evolution has occurred elsewhere in the universe and not just on earth.
			<br /><br />It is ironic that, while specifically looking for signs of intelligent life, "SETIans" have missed the obvious implications of the complex patterns of life right here on earth. Specifically, that the many non-random patterns which characterize life and living things on this planet are themselves signals that there is an intelligent designer behind these patterns.
			<br /><br />The evolutionary faithful are unmoved by this argument, yet it is exactly this argument which they offer as the rationale for the search for life beyond earth. Some will spend their lives looking for a sign of intelligent life behind the patterns of radio emissions from space, but never apply this same reasoning to life on earth. To do so would lead them to a totally different conclusion about the origin and meaning of life than they currently hold.
			<br /><br />In his short answer, Peter Backus even admits that at SETI they really don't even know what kind of pattern to look for. Should they look for a binary code of ones and zeros such as is used in our computers, or a symbolic language or pictures? He observes that "other encoding schemes have been suggested, but in truth scientists do not know what to expect. That is part of what makes SETI so interesting."
			<br /><br />Their faith tells them life is out there. Their logic tells them generally what to look for - even that is uncertain. So they keep listening for the right signal, either unaware of, or willfully deaf to, the chorus of signals directed at them here on earth by God saying, "I am here, I am here, I am here." But, sadly, they have neither ears to hear nor eyes to see, and so continue to miss the obvious even while searching for it.
			<br /><br />>Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="is-god-dead-or-just-improbable">
		<title>Is God Dead? Or Just Improbable?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/GodProbable.jpg" />
			History does seem to repeat itself. The old 1960s philosophy that "God is dead" has been updated in the new millennium and is now marketed as "God is not probable." That is, one can't say for sure whether God is alive or dead without one actually being God. But by using a statistical method, supposedly one can estimate how probable or likely it is that God exists. In the July 2004 issue of Scientific American magazine, Michael Shermer reviews a recent book that calculates the likelihood, or chance, of God existing as 67%. This surprisingly high, better than 50-50, chance of God being real does not sit well with Shermer who asserts that "religious faith [has] little or nothing to do with probabilities, evidence and logic." Shermer puts his own values into the formula and produces the much more, shall we say, skeptical probability that God exists, of 2%. Apparently both God's popularity as well as His chance of even being real is down among the ranks of skeptics.
			<br /><br />Shermer graciously allows for a 2% chance that he could be wrong about God. I'm sure in reality he believes the chance is 0% but he wants to convey the impression that, compared to the optimistic figure of 67%, it is highly improbable that God exists, and that people of faith believe in God despite evidence, logic and probabilities. He gives the 2% figure to avoid the criticism that to know absolutely that God does not exist one would have to know everything - but if one knows everything, then one would, in fact, be God, something that even a skeptic like Shermer is hesitant to claim.
			<br /><br />What he seems to not realize is that a 2% chance means one chance out of 50 that God exists. That means his estimate of God's existence is actually much, much more probable to be true than his own evolutionary faith that a single small protein molecule, made up of specific amino acid building blocks, would form by random chance. Such calculations about the chances of simple protein formation have been widely discussed and vary from one incomprehensible number to another, depending on the size of the protein and other assumptions. A number like one chance in 1040,000 has been calculated by Sir Fred Hoyle as the probability of a single small protein forming by random processes. Henry Morris, in his book The Biblical Basis of Modern Science says, "This number is so miniscule as to be equivalent to zero. That is, there is no chance whatever that it could have happened by chance." By contrast, then, the figure of 1 chance in 50 given by Shermer for God's existence seems like absolute certainty when considered in the light of the impossibility of even a simple protein forming by chance, let alone the entire "tree" of evolutionary life-forms. Even a skeptic's worst case probability of God's existence is billions and billions and billions of times more likely than even the best-case scenario of the biochemical evolution of a single protein. Whose faith then is the more improbable?
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes
			<br /><br />1 Shermer, M. "God's Number is Up." Scientific American, July 2004, p 46.
			<br />2 Hoyle, F. and Wickramisinghe, C. "Where Microbes Boldly Went." New Scientist. 91:412-415, 1981.
			<br />3 Morris, H. The Biblical Basis of Modern Science. Baker Book House, 1984.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="et-please-call-home">
		<title>E.T., Please Call Home</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/ETcallHome.jpg" />
			NASA recently sent two probes to Mars to look for water. Finding water on Mars is important because believers of the evolutionary church understand that life is not possible without water. They must either find existing life, evidence of past life, or conditions that allow life to evolve outside of earth if they hope to convince unbelievers that life on earth evolved from nonliving chemicals by chance. Finding life outside of earth would bring instant fame, money, Nobel prizes and the thanks of the congregation who believe in the triune god of evolution - time, chance and natural selection.
			<br /><br />The homily goes like this: Earth is not unique. It is a small speck orbiting an ordinary star in a galaxy of billions and billions of stars that must also have planets orbiting them just as earth orbits our sun. Thousands if not millions of planets just like earth must exist in the vastness of space, and surely the conditions that gave rise to life here on earth must be present many places in the universe. If life on earth has had time to develop to the point we can explore nearby planets, then it is certain that this has also happened by evolution on other planets. In fact life must be common in the cosmos. Or so the argument goes.
			<br /><br />Thinking people may ask, if this story is true then where is all the life? Everywhere we look and as far as we can sense with our best instruments, there is no life. There are elements, energy, even water - but no life. Where would E.T. call when he phones home? Where is the catalog of earth-like planets with conditions that would have allowed for life to start and evolve? There isn't one. If faith is the substance of things hoped for, the assurance of things not seen (Heb. 1:1), then the faith of evolutionary believers is as immense as the heavens. They are sure that the life they hope to find is really there, even though they have absolutely no evidence that it exists.
			<br /><br />Recently a new evolutionary sect has developed which recognizes that wherever in space we look there is no life. But, rather than questioning their belief in evolution, they turn the problem on its head. In the book entitled Rare Earth, Peter D. Ward and Donald Brownlee suggests that the conditions necessary for complex life to evolve are more rare than the conditions necessary for "simple" life to arise. Therefore we would not expect to easily find signs of complex life. So our inability to contact life outside earth does not mean that life is not there. This simply begs the question and does not change the fact that there is so far no evidence to support their belief. Is life common or rare in the universe? The evolutionary church allows you to have faith in either idea as long as you don't challenge the fundamental doctrine of life beyond earth. But unfortunately so far for E.T., there is no one home to take his call.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote
			<br /><br />1 Ward, P.D. and Brownlee, D. Rare Earth: Why Complex Life is Uncommon in the Universe. Copernicus. Springer-Verlag, 2000.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="which-came-first">
		<title>Which Came First?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Protein_DNA_HumanCell.jpg" />
			Consider for a moment the lowly protein. We take proteins for granted because they are produced and act automatically in our cells. Much is known about how proteins are made and how they function. But the harder question is: Where did proteins come from? Proteins are made from instructions in DNA but proteins are needed to make DNA. So we might ask: Which came first - the DNA or the protein? The answer is that neither came first. In order to have either DNA or protein, both are required.
			<br /><br />The evolutionary explanation for how proteins formed is that lightning reacted with chemicals in the atmosphere of the "early earth" to create amino acids. This formed a thin soup of chemicals in warm tide pools. Amino acids joined together to make proteins which then became part of fat globules that then became living cells. Easy, isn't it? It seems so to those of the evolutionary faith and to those with little scientific background.
			<br /><br />The environment of the "early" earth would have been harsh. High levels of radiation would break proteins down as quickly as they formed, and the heat from volcanoes would also destroy proteins. But there is another, more fundamental, problem with the evolutionary scheme for protein formation, a problem that would prevent proteins from ever being formed to begin with. Chemical reversibility.
			<br /><br />Proteins can be both made and broken apart depending on the chemical conditions. One of those conditions is the presence or absence of water (H2O). When amino acids join together, a molecule of water (H2O) is released and a chemical bond is formed. This water has to be removed before the next amino acid is added, otherwise the next bond will not form or the previous bond may be broken. This means that the last place one would predict a protein could form is in the early ocean because the chemical reactions forming the protein would be immediately reversed by all the water! Dr. A.E. Wilder-Smith in his book, The Natural Sciences Know Nothing of Evolution, makes exactly this point. The formation of functioning proteins by chance natural processes in the "early ocean" would be a totally futile chemical exercise. As soon as one chemical bond would be made, it would be broken.
			<br /><br />What does this mean for the faith of the evolutionist? Probably not much. Evolutionary believers have immense faith in the unseen hand of chance and millions of years of time for unlikely events to happen over and over. Maybe proteins came first, then DNA; or perhaps it was DNA and then protein. It doesn't really matter for the evolutionist since time and chance can make both. But if you must already have both to have either one, then they could not have evolved in sequence, one after the other. Nor could DNA and protein have evolved in different locations since they each require the other to function in a cell. No, to have both DNA and protein in the same place at the same time to form a living cell would take&hellip;God.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote
			<br /><br />1 Wilder-Smith, A. E. The Natural Sciences Know Nothing of Evolution. Master Books, San Diego, CA. 1981.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="avian-olympians">
		<title>Avian Olympians</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/AvianOlympics.jpg" />
			Every four years, athletes from all over the world compete to represent their nations in the Olympic Games. The games originally began in Greece where athletes competed in events such as boxing and wrestling. The modern Olympic Games have today become a forum for national pride in addition to a celebration of athletic achievement. The winners of the Olympic Marathon race set the standard for endurance and dedication for all Olympic athletes. Running the 26 miles 385 yards takes incredible determination and aerobic conditioning. Such top Olympic runners must train for years to reach this elite level
			<br /><br />As impressive as human athletic achievements are, one does not have to look very hard to find examples of incredible endurance among the birds, feats no human could match. Take, for example, the Pacific Golden Plover. This small bird sets out each winter on an 88-hour non-stop migration from the Arctic Circle to Hawaii. It is a non-swimmer and does not rest or sleep during its migration, losing 50% of its body weight during the journey. Even more incredibly, the Plover's chicks mature in the Arctic and make exactly the same migration after its parents, but without instruction in navigation over the open ocean where an error of only one degree would cause them to miss their destination. Whether the Plover uses the sun or stars or both to guide it is not known.
			<br /><br />The Robin covers about 40 miles a day during its migration, a distance few people could cover in one day unassisted, let alone for 78 days in a row as the Robin does. In experiments with homing birds taken from their home range and released, the Lesser Yellowlegs covered the 1900 miles between Cape Cod, Massachusetts, and their island home of Martinique in just six days. An average of 316 miles per day!
			<br /><br />The physical stamina and aerobic efficiency of birds that migrate up to seven thousand miles is impressive enough. But add to this the ability to navigate to precise locations over unfamiliar ground, or "home in" on a familiar location from thousands of miles away. One begins to wonder how an evolutionary process could "create" these abilities. It stretches the limits of credibility to believe that undirected chance mechanisms of evolution produced the organs and systems which birds need for long distance migrations, let alone the pre-programmed knowledge of how to use the sun, stars or landmarks to navigate to a place they have never seen before. Since birds don't acquire the physical or navigational abilities for migration by practice and learning, isn't it more plausible that these abilities are a result of intentional, conscious design rather than undirected chance?
			<br /><br />In bird migration we come to appreciate that God understands distance, time, and physical needs for survival, as well as how to use the sun, moon and stars as navigational signs. If He programs birds to fly with such endurance, can He not also help us to "run with endurance the race set before us"? (Heb. 12:1).
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes
			<br /><br />1 Martin J. Incredible Creatures that Defy Evolution II. Exploration Films.com
			<br />2 Tyne J, A.J. Berger. Fundamentals of Ornithology. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1976, pp. 362-363.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-new-straw-man">
		<title>The New Straw Man</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Scarecrow_StrawMan.jpg" />
			I recently saw a sarcastic bumper sticker which read, "What's next, gravity?" The reference is to the opposition by Christians to public school indoctrination of students with the religious beliefs of evolution. The inference is that "you Christians are dumb because you reject the absolute truth of evolution and if we tolerate this then perhaps your next attack will be on the validity of gravity." This very common debating technique is called knocking down the "straw man." The opposing position is first described as challenging what everyone knows is true, showing it is in fact true, and then highlighting how silly it is to believe what the opponent is said to believe. I am not aware of any Christians who challenge the reality of gravity, so this line is generally limited to sarcastic bumper stickers.
			<br /><br />The more popular straw man actually used against Christians today is that "you Christians believe that the world is flat." Most Christians are surprised to be told that they believe this. What follows is a reference to the "Flat Earth Society" and the verse in Isaiah 11:12 referring to the "four corners of the earth." This is meant to show how scientifically unsophisticated and backward Christians are, and how they would rather believe the Bible than what is observably true.
			<br /><br />Well, how do we know the world is round? Can you give at least one way we know from observation that it is? Here are two ways. During an eclipse of the moon, the shadow of the earth falling on the moon is curved. This can only be true if the earth is a sphere.
			<br /><br />Secondly, when seeing a tall ship approach from the horizon, what is seen first is the very top of the ship and not the outline of the entire ship. This could only be true if the ship at the horizon were coming over the surface of a curved sphere. So the earth is a sphere despite the figurative language used in Isaiah 11:12 and the belief of a very few people to the contrary.
			<br /><br />There is no conflict here between the Bible and observable truth. In fact, in Isaiah 40:22, the prophet speaks of the "circle of the earth" and, as the earth rotates to produce our daily cycle, the circle of the horizon never changes. This could only be true of a sphere.
			<br /><br />The use of debate rhetoric against Christians is reminiscent of the political arena where intellectual honesty often falls by the wayside in favor of name calling and deliberate distortion of facts. What is needed is thoughtful discussion on the question of origins. Phillip Johnson, in his book Darwin on Trial, asserts that the question of how life originated is still open for debate in the 21st century despite the dogmatic intolerance of the adherents to evolution. Isaiah was correct again when, on behalf of the Lord, he said, "Come now, and let us reason together" (Isa. 1:18).
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote
			<br /><br />1 Johnson, Phillip. Darwin on Trial. InterVarsity Press. Downers Grove, IL, 1993.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="too-hot-too-cold-ah-just-right">
		<title>Too Hot, Too Cold.... ah Just Right!</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/thermostat.jpg" />
			A thermostat is an example of a mechanical feedback loop. When set to a particular temperature, it senses changes in air temperature and reacts to defend the setpoint temperature by turning the heating or cooling system on or off.
			<br /><br />Living things use the same principles to maintain body temperature, blood pressure, blood sugar, adequate blood calcium levels, to control bone growth and regulate the supply of energy in cells - just to name a very, very few.
			<br /><br />In many cases, the regulation of enzyme activity or level of minerals is exquisitely controlled within a very small range. Intelligent people designed and built the thermostat and the cruise control in an automobile. People also determine the setpoint of the mechanism. But where did biological feedback loops come from, and who or what determined their setpoints? Did the loops just design themselves by evolution?
			<br /><br />Describing a feedback loop in a living cell or organism is simple. It is much harder to understand exactly how nonliving chemicals sense a condition, compare it to a pre-set level and then react to bring the condition back to where it should be. How do mere chemicals know what should be? We speak about how the body "controls" blood sugar by directing the liver to make and release sugar at night and by releasing insulin after we eat, causing muscle cells to pick up sugar from the blood. But people understand why keeping blood sugar in a certain range is good and what specifically the range of blood sugar should be. This is a type of understanding that chemicals themselves just do not have.
			<br /><br />Partial feedback loops are of little to no benefit. If the body could sense high blood sugar or high blood pressure and yet not be able to react to change, it is of little survival value. In fact, when feedback loops don't work, we call it "disease" - like diabetes or hypertension. These diseases decrease rather than increase survival. According to evolutionary doctrine, each small change in structure and function must be of survival value to be passed on to future generations. Yet for a feedback loop to function and be of survival value, all the parts must simultaneously exist in the same living cell or body. So how could an entire feedback loop ever evolve when partial loops actually decrease survival?
			<br /><br />Evolution requires adherents to believe by faith, without proof, that the thousands of biological feedback loops evolved independently and sequentially over time with no intelligent input. In essence, to believe that the spring designed the thermostat. This is not what happens. Mechanical and biological machines just don't make themselves. If feedback loops did not make themselves, and people didn't make them, isn't it more reasonable to believe the biblical statement that "all things have been created by Him," that is, God the Son (Col. 1:16)? He is the only one who has the intelligence to design, the power to make and the understanding to determine the setpoint of living feedback loops. "Honey, can you turn the heat up?"
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-web-of-life">
		<title>The Web of Life</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/WebLife.jpg" />
			By early Fall in the "sunflower state" of Kansas where I live, millions of tons of wheat, corn, beans, and yes, sunflowers, have been produced by the incredible biological machine called a green plant. Peter Ray of Stanford University describes a plant in engineering terms as a "device for capturing the energy of sunlight and using it through the process of photosynthesis, to convert carbon dioxide into organic carbon compounds [sugars] from which the substance of life can be manufactured."1 The root, stem and leaves are just "the equipment necessary to make photosynthesis successful" in that they absorb water and minerals from the soil and provide a place, within the leaves, for the finely tuned biochemistry of photosynthesis to happen.
			<br /><br />Since the late 1700s it has been known that the actual organic substance of the plant comes, not from the soil, but from carbon dioxide which is part of air. Incredibly then, the millions of tons of wheat, corn and other crops made of carbon-containing chemicals appear in the fields each year literally out of thin air. But plants don't just absorb sunlight and chemically trap atmospheric carbon; they also release molecular oxygen (O2) as a byproduct of photosynthesis and serve as a food source for animals and humans. Indeed, animal and human life on earth would not be possible without photosynthesis. So the plant is the foundational machine in a larger web of living machines which depend on each other to sustain life on earth.
			<br /><br />Plants take in sunlight, carbon dioxide and water, producing organic sugars and oxygen. Animals and humans consume plants and use oxygen to "burn" the organic sugars as fuel. They also exhale carbon dioxide, the very molecule needed by the plant as raw material for its life and growth. Although oversimplified, this example is still sufficient to illustrate that the "web of life" is not a random development. It is not only that each part of the web is a complete, functioning device that is compelling and astonishing, but that each part has a purpose to sustain a larger, integrated and co-dependent system. The existence of purposeful relationship and interdependence between parts in a larger system is evidence of conscious, rational design and not unconscious chance.
			<br /><br />Consider an electric razor. It must have a means to capture, transform and transmit energy to the cutting blades. Integrated within the housing along with circuits and various gears, shafts and brushes, is an assembly of individual machines functioning in a system for a specific purpose, created by conscious intelligence. So it is with the biological world and the web of life. This is exactly why Peter Ray cannot help but use engineering terms and examples when describing the plant and why even staunch evolutionary believers cannot keep from using the word "designed" when describing living things. One must concede that the biological world appears to be designed because it is designed, or else bear the burden of proof as to why the web of life even exists at all.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote
			<br /><br />1 Ray, Peter Martin. The Living Plant. Second edition. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc. 1972. p 1.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="darwin-you-have-failed-us">
		<title>Darwin, You Have Failed Us!</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/CharlesDarwin.jpg" />
			<em>After decades of preaching Darwinian evolution, one of it's missionaries admits failure. </em>
			<br /><br />Every so often there appears in print an article that reveals the inner turmoil of the evolutionary believer who has faithfully devoted his life to following the precepts of Darwinism and to passing on the faith to future generations, only to see no fruit from his labors. Such is the case expressed in a short viewpoint article in the British journal The Lancet by Australian R.V. Short.1 In this psalm of lament entitled "Darwin, have I failed you?" professor Short confesses his sadness at not being able to convert any of the 150 medical students enrolled in his class on human evolution from their misguided religious beliefs to his own religion of Darwinism.
			<br /><br />Despite having the advantages of unopposed authority as the instructor, editorial control over the course content, the power of the grade book, and the expressed intent to "correct the misconceptions" of his students, there were no changes in the beliefs of his students when measured by comparing answers to an anonymous questionnaire given before and then after the class was completed.
			<br /><br />Almost tearfully professor Short observes, "To my utter dismay, there were no statistically significant changes in any of the answers to any of the questions." Sensing that he had fallen short in gaining converts for the Darwinian faith, he says, "I was shattered." But taking solace from the knowledge that he had "sown a few seeds of the truth" during the class, professor Short invokes the Darwinian confession of faith, solemnly intoning, "I believe in the truth of evolution and still regard it as the most exciting fundamental concept that underpins the whole of biological thinking."
			<br /><br />While Short feels he failed Darwin, the truth is that Darwin has failed us. In the 145 years since the publication of Darwin's book On the Origin of Species, the precepts of biological evolution have been adopted, in large part, by those who have no other faith, no other way to understand how the world came to be, why it is the way it is, and where it is going. In a sense, biological evolution is the faith of religious orphans. Aside from failing to provide clear and convincing evidence of the truth of the spontaneous formation of life and of molecules to man evolution, Darwinism has failed to provide any foundation for human morality and justice. 2 Hitler, Stalin and other tyrants used Darwinism to justify untold human suffering and the pursuit of ultimate power.
			<br /><br />Darwinism has failed to provide purpose and value to individuals, hence the "right" to kill unborn children by abortion and perhaps soon the "right" to practice euthanasia and physician-assisted suicide. It has also failed as a basis for just government, economics, politics and human freedom, and it has failed to provide peace both individually in the human heart and in society as is clearly seen in the continuously growing prison inmate population and ongoing conflicts in every part of the globe. We have not failed Darwin; he has failed us.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.Endnotes
			<br />1 Short, R.V. "Darwin, have I failed you?" The Lancet 343:528- 529, 1994.
			<br />2 Johnson, P.E. Defeating Darwinism by Opening Minds. InterVarsity Press, 1997.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="there-are-all-kinds-of-problems-in-the-bible-for-example-where-did-cain-get-his-wife">
		<title>There are all kinds of problems in the Bible. For example, where did Cain get his wife?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/cainwife.jpg" />
			For those not familiar with the Bible, it tells us that God created a man and a woman to begin the human race. Interestingly, scientists who study genetics have come to the conclusion that they can see an unbroken line back to the first woman. They call her Lucy. The Bible says her name was Eve.
			<br /><br />Adam and Eve had a son and named him Cain (Genesis 4:1). Unfortunately, Cain's story is a sad one. The first son murdered his own brother in an envious rage, and set up the first false religion (Jude 11).
			<br /><br />The Bible says that Cain married a wife. People who distrust the Bible have asked where this wife came from if there was only one family. Of course, believing in evolution doesn't solve that problem either. Who did "Lucy's children" marry?
			<br /><br />The simple answer is that Cain must have married a sister. Of course this is not something allowed today. In fact it was forbidden in the Bible in the days of Moses (Leviticus 18:9) but that was a long time after Cain.
			<br /><br />One of the reasons intermarrying within your immediate family is this: there are damaged parts to our genetic code and, as time goes by, that damage in the human genetic code keeps getting worse. But these damaged parts do not always appear because they are usually "recessive."
			<br /><br />If we marry close relatives, there is a much higher possibility that any children will suffer from these damaged areas called mutants. This is becaused the gene in both near relatives is damaged at the same place (on locus).
			<br /><br />Of course that wasn't true at the beginning. In fact the Bible tells us that people in those days regularly lived many hundreds of years, some almost to 1000!
			<br /><br />However, by the time God had to destroy the world with a flood because the human race had become so wicked, it was obvious that man's lifespan was getting shorter and shorter. At the time of the flood, only one family was saved by obeying God and building a large boat.
			<br /><br />When this family began to intermarry, we see the recorded lifespan drop dramatically down to just over one hundred years. It continued to decrease until it reached the level where it is today.
			<br /><br />The Medici family, one of the dominant forces in the Middle Ages, intermarried in order to maintain their wealth and power. Arthur Custance writes:
			<br /><br />"The Medici family - beginning with Giovanni di Bicci de Medici (1360-1429) and ending, in one line, with Catherine de Medici (1519-1589) who married Henry II of France - provides us with another instance where inbreeding clearly affected viability. The members of the family for successive generations traced through two lives lived shorter and shorter, with the notable exception of Catherine herself. These two lines are given below with their life spans indicated by years rather than dates, to simplify the figures."
			<br /><br />In one line from Giovanni de Bicci de Medici we have: Cosimo (75 years), Piero (53 years), Lorenzo the Magnificent (43 years), Piero (32 years), and Lorenzo (27 years) and ending with Catherine and her brother Alessandro (27 years). In the other line: Lorenzo (45 years), Pier Francesco (46 years), Lorenzo iL Popolano (40 years), Pier Francesco (39 years), and Lorenzo (33 years).
			<br /><br />Custance also quotes Willard F. Hollander, in an article titled, "Lethal Heredity." He comments:
			<br /><br />"Sometimes a mutation is so radical that nothing can be done to prolong the animal's life to maturity. This is what is known as a lethal mutation. Often it kills the animal while it is still an embryo. Most lethal mutations are recessive, however, and are carried unsuspected by normal appearing animals&hellip;
			<br /><br />"The quickest way to expose lethal traits is by intense and continued inbreeding. In man such matings are generally illegal or tabu; the experience of the race indicates bad results&hellip;the outcome is generally detrimental. When inbreeding begins, the heredity seems to be breaking down. All sorts of defects and weaknesses appear. The average life span decreases. After a few generations the family often becomes extinct" (Scientific American, July 1952, pp. 59-60).
			<br /><br />Thus it seems that Cain married a sister, something that is forbidden today for very good reason.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="is-it-true-that-god-can-do-anything-can-he-make-a-rock-that-is-too-big-for-him-to-lift">
		<title>Is it true that God can do anything? Can He make a rock that is too big for Him to lift?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/GlobeinHands.jpg" />
			When people say they believe that God can do anything, they mean he can do anything that is consistent with his character. in fact the Bible says there are some things that God cannot do.
			<strong>GOD CANNOT DENY HIMSELF</strong>
			For example, we read, "If we believe not, yet God remains faithful: he cannot deny himself" (2 Timothy 2:13). In other words, even if we don't care about God, he still cares about us! He gives the atheist his breakfast - even the mental ability to think up silly arguments against God's existence!
			<br /><br />Jesus said to his followers, "Love your enemies, bless those who curse you, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who despitefully use you, and persecute you; that you may be the children of your Father who is in heaven: for he makes his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sends rain on the just and on the unjust" (Matthew 5:44-45). God shows daily kindness to those who are his enemies.
			<strong>GOD CANNOT LIE</strong>
			We also read "of eternal life, which God, that cannot lie, promised before the world began" (Titus 1:2). Isn't that a great thing! When God makes promises, he cannot afterwards change his mind.
			<br /><br />In another place, the Bible tells us that God not only said he will save people who come to him; he also swears an oath so we can be very sure. "God, willing more abundantly to show the unchangeability of his counsel, confirmed it by an oath: that by two unchangeable things, in which it was impossible for God to lie, we might have a strong consolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold on the hope set before us: which hope we have as an anchor of the soul" (Heb. 6:17-19).
			<strong>GOD CANNOT BE TEMPTED</strong>
			The Bible also tells us that "God cannot be tempted with evil, neither does he tempt anyone" (James 1:13). Unlike the gods of Greek and Roman mythology, the God of the Bible is holy. He always does what is right.
			<br /><br />Which reminds me of the original question: Can God make a stone larger than he can lift? Well, I know this much: If you harden your heart against God until it's like a stone, even almighty God himself can't lift it up to heaven. That's why the Bible warns: "Today if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts" (Hebrews 3:15).
			<br /><br />"He, that being often reproved hardens his neck, shall suddenly be destroyed, and that without remedy" (Proverbs 29:1).?
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="scientific-secrets">
		<title>Scientific Secrets</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/ScienceSecrets.jpg" />
			<em>The "facts" need to be brought into focus.</em>
			<br /><br />Science has many secrets. Not deep, dark, conspiratorial secrets, but practical secrets that are well-known to trained scientists yet not often revealed to the public, and for good reason. Scientists like to project an aura of authority and calm, unbiased rationality, which might be in jeopardy if these "secrets" were widely appreciated. This is especially true in a world where scientific proof is expected and where scientific arguments influence everyday life - think global warming or recycling.
			<br /><br />Almost all laboratory science at the university and industrial levels happens without reference to evolutionary theory. It is only in the paper writing stage that authors often search for some evolutionary framework in which to set their results, if only to satisfy reviewers. So the first secret is that evolution is not at all the main driving force in modern science. The rare exceptions are those who claim to specifically study evolution and who must have something that generates research funding so they can keep their jobs. In truth, the vast majority of science is driven by the desire to know how the world works now and not how it supposedly evolved.
			<br /><br />Another trade secret is that science usually doesn't work. In fact, an investigator must work hard to fine-tune conditions to make it work. Less time is spent generating results than time spent working out these "optimal" conditions. Once the investigator believes the results are real, then interpretation begins. One key part of interpretation is developing different ideas to explain the results. These then form the basis for the design of new experiments, whose conditions must once again be optimized before the results can be believed. And so it continues.
			<br /><br />The third practical secret of science is that it must tell a good story. Science is, in essence, explanatory. If bits of information are woven together in a way that makes sense to the hearer, the more plausible the story is as an explanation of an observation - even if it later turns out to be wrong. In practice, a coherent story can suggest new experiments to perform and even predict their results. But where scientific storytelling goes wrong is in the popular media where speculation becomes fact and where extrapolation is too easily held forth as truth. If a story is repeated often enough it starts to sound true. Carl Sagan and David Attenborough of Cosmos and Life on Earth fame, respectively, each made a second career out of weaving plausible-sounding stories which were often more philosophical than fact-based.
			<br /><br />There are other secrets in science. For example, statistics can be used to "prove" almost anything the investigator desires, and proof in medical trials is different from that in a laboratory. In the final analysis though, science is an immensely powerful tool, but it is affected by philosophical and political agendas because it is performed by people who bring their own presuppositions to it. My advice is to be skeptical of scientific claims, especially in popular media, until you know the secrets.
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="readers-guide-to-the-origins-debate">
		<title>Reader's guide to the origins debate</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/origin_evol_life.gif" />
			<em>Looking for some deeper resources at the issues surrounding the Evolution/Creation/Intelligent Design issue? Here are some well recommended books.</em>
			<br /><br />In his 1999 book How the News Makes us Dumb1, historian C. John Sommerville observes that the greatest problem with today's news coverage is not so much that it is biased (which it is), as that it is daily. As a consequence, news is reduced to the lowest common denominator, often without context, and shortened into quickly digestible "sound bytes." Accessing news and information today is not difficult. But coming to a reasoned understanding of issues such as the global warming controversy or the creation/evolution/intelligent design debate using information from standard media outlets is essentially impossible. There is just no substitute for in-depth knowledge gained by reading several book-length arguments on a topic and chewing on the strengths and weaknesses of the arguments before forming a personal conclusion.
			<br /><br />As a scientist and avid reader, I am sometimes asked to recommend books about the creation/evolution/design debate for those without a background in science but with a hunger to understand. Just as a good meal has several courses, so, too, will a study of the debate. As an appetizer, read Phillip E. Johnson's book Defeating Darwinism by Opening Minds2. Written by a law professor, this easy-to-read book lays out a framework for thinking about the debate and for understanding each side's definition of key words like "science" and "evolution." Johnson points out how the issues and participants have been so stereotyped since the popular play and movie Inherit the Wind - a dramatized version of the 1925 Scopes "monkey trial" in Dayton, Tennessee - that valid criticisms of the scientific problems and biases of Darwinism are drowned out. Love and reason triumph over prejudice and religious bigotry, so the story goes. But this is not what actually happened in Dayton. For the real story of the trial, read Marvin Olasky's excellent book, Monkey Business3.
			<br /><br />The main course requires one to bite into the meat of the criticisms of Darwinian evolution and may require some determined chewing to digest. Phillip E. Johnson's Darwin on Trial4 is worth the effort. It is the most concise and thoughtful book in print on the key issues. A lighter, more personal-discovery style course is found in Lee Strobel's The Case for a Creator5. This readable book follows the author in a journey of discovery as he interviews many of the leading critics of modern Darwinian evolution and presents their views. Phillip E. Johnson serves up another meaty course designed to distinguish scientific fact from philosophy-laden interpretation in The Wedge of Truth6. Because interpretations influenced by philosophy often become "facts" through the media sound bite megaphone, learning to distinguish between the two may eventually split apart the intellectual foundation of Darwinism.
			<br /><br />While I prefer to focus on written material because "reading is to the mind what exercise is to the body,"7 there are two DVDs that make a wonderful two-layer dessert for the mind. These are The Privileged Planet and Unlocking The Mystery Of Life, both from Illustra Media8. Bon app&eacute;tit!
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes:
			<br /><br />1 C. John Sommerville, How the News Makes Us Dumb (Downer's Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 1999).
			<br />2 Phillip E. Johnson, Defeating Darwinism By Opening Minds (Downer's Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 1997).
			<br />3 Marvin Olasky &amp; John Perry, Monkey Business (Nashville, TN: Broadman &amp; Holman Publishers, 2005).
			<br />4 Phillip E. Johnson, Darwin On Trial (Downer's Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 1993).
			<br />5 Lee Strobel, The Case For A Creator (Grand Rapids, MI: Zondervan, 2004).
			<br />6 Phillip E. Johnson, The Wedge of Truth (Downer's Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2000).
			<br />7 Sir Richard Steele (1672 - 1729). www.quotationspage.com
			<br />8 www.illustramedia.com
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="survivor">
		<title>Survivor</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/JustFlipEm-HorsshoeCrab.jpg" />
			<em>The horseshoe crab: just lucky?</em>
			<br /><br />The North American horseshoe crab (Limulus polyphemus) is a real survivor. The standard evolution-based interpretation of fossil evidence is that horseshoe crabs have survived virtually unchanged for 445 million years despite living through times of massive geologic and environmental upheaval.1 Recently, some conservationists have claimed that the horseshoe crab may need the help of humans to survive.2 But does it? Why would such a stout survivor need our help when it seems to have done just fine on its own?
			<br /><br /><br />One of only four species of horseshoe crab worldwide, Limulus polyphemus is a mild-mannered arthropod which wears its horseshoe-shaped skeleton on the outside and bears a long tail or telson, which it uses to right itself when flipped upside down by waves. It lives along the Atlantic coast from Maine to Florida, and in the Gulf of Mexico as far south as the Yucatan Peninsula. Every year during May and June, millions of adults migrate to sandy beaches like those in Delaware Bay to spawn. Each female can lay between 80,000 and 100,000 eggs over several days and can live as long as 20 years. This massive release of horseshoe crab eggs not only ensures its own survival but also that of thousands of birds who eat the eggs as a vital energy source on their northward migration. The horseshoe crab is also a favored bait of fishermen, and its blood is part of a test to detect bacterial contamination in vaccines for human use.
			<br /><br />But the horseshoe crab has survived more than human economic use and the predation of its eggs by birds. The geologic record shows that the earth has changed tremendously over time. A key testament to this change is that over 99 percent of all species of animals that ever lived are now extinct. There is also geologic evidence of a time past in which 95 percent of all ocean-dwelling species went extinct.3 And the horseshoe crab survived all of this without human help. No doubt the simple, rigid tail is one of many keys to its ability to survive and continue to reproduce.
			<br /><br />Despite this track record for survival, a horseshoe crab conservation campaign has begun in Delaware Bay which is called "Just Flip 'em". It asks beach goers to flip over upside down horseshoe crabs to help them get back into the ocean. Yet the animal already possesses a well designed solution to the problem in its long, rigid tail and biologists are still unsure whether horseshoe crab populations are declining and might benefit from such a strategy or not. Flip 'em? Sure - it may not help much in the case of the horseshoe crab because they are survivors, but it makes us feel good to help animals. And since all people bear the image of God, however faded, it is not surprising that some respond to the ancient - but still compelling - command to cultivate and keep the garden even though they may have forgotten the One who planted it to begin with.
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes:
			<br /><br />1 Royal Ontario Museum, "Oldest Horseshoe Crab Fossil Found, 445 Million Years Old," Science Daily (Feb. 8, 2008), web link
			<br />2 Jennifer H. Mattei &amp; Mark A. Beckey, "The Horseshoe Crab Conundrum: Can we Harvest and Conserve?" Wrack Lines 8:1 (Spring/Summer 2008), web link
			<br />3 Microsoft&reg; Encarta&reg; Online Encyclopedia 2009, s.v. "Extinction (biology)," web link
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="synthetic-life">
		<title>Synthetic Life</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/CultureDishScience.jpg" />
			<em>Unintelligent design?</em>
			<br /><br />Is it possible to make life from scratch using just its raw materials? After all, living and non-living things are made from the same atoms and elements - they differ only in the quantities and arrangements of those atoms. A recent History Channel (THC) program called "How Life Began" leaves the impression that life "formed" relatively easily based on standard chemistry. If this is true, why not deliberately make a living cell in the laboratory using standard methods and readily available biological molecules? Take as many living cells as you want and break them apart into their component proteins, fats, nucleic acids, and inorganic salts. Then reassemble them into at least one living cell. Why not? Because it turns out that making synthetic life is not so easy after all. But if it was easy for random chance and basic chemistry to produce life originally, then why is it so hard for highly intelligent and experienced researchers to produce synthetic life on purpose?
			<br /><br />To date, no one has succeeded in making synthetic life, but there are several research groups working toward this goal.1 One group hopes to make a "minimal" living cell by starting with a "simple" bacterial cell and cutting down its 528 genes to the bare minimum for survival. Other groups are starting from scratch and hoping to assemble something that just meets the definition of life, which itself is controversial.2 Along the way, they will certainly learn more about how cells work, while others hope to gain insight into what "primitive" cells may have been like.
			<br /><br />What is the reasoning behind these efforts to create synthetic life? The premise is that if life can be constructed by just putting parts together in the correct way, then life is not really special. It is a lucky accident of chemistry, and there is no need to suggest that a Creator was behind life in the beginning. Using this reasoning, building a Ford Model T car using parts out of modern Ford cars means Henry Ford never existed, and the original Model T just made itself out of random metal parts.3 If one day there appeared on your driveway a new Ford pickup truck, is the best explanation of how it got there that it simply made itself? This is what Isaac Newton once told an atheist friend who wondered aloud who had made the exquisite model of the solar system in Newton's study. "No one made it" Newton said. "It made itself". The absurdity of Newton's point is clear. Someone had to have made the model solar system, the pickup truck, and, yes, life.
			<br /><br />The History Channel program ends with the admission that it doesn't really matter if we can't figure out how to make life synthetically after years of dedicated, intelligent effort. Life may have formed spontaneously in space and been seeded on earth by meteors, or the "Earth" must have figured out how to make life on its own because, after all, we're here aren't we?"
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 P. Barry, "Life From Scratch," Science News Online, vol. 173, no. 2 (week of Jan. 12, 2008), http://www.sciencenews.org/
			<br />2 M. Madiagan and J. Martinko, Brock Biology of Microorganisms, 11th ed. (Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall, 2005).
			<br />3 J.C. Lennox, God's Undertaker: Has Science Buried God? (Oxford, England: Lion, 2007).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="purpose-by-design">
		<title>Purpose By Design</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/HumanCells.jpg" />
			<em>Can mindless chance think ahead?</em>
			<br /><br />Purpose in living systems is evidence of intelligence applied. Human stem cells are important during both development and adult life. Therefore, one could argue that only intelligence can explain the purpose-driven life of the stem cell. The standard biological explanation, however, is that stem cells evolved by a process devoid of purpose or intelligent direction; that evolution "created" complex living stem cells which serve important purposes but which were, themselves, not created on purpose. Recently, a surprising new purpose has been described for adult stem cells which makes it even more difficult to believe that such critically important cells evolved by purposeless chance.
			<br /><br />Stem cells are unspecialized cells that can divide and produce highly specialized cells.1 During embryonic development, stem cells have a clear purpose in producing the cells that eventually become the liver, heart, lungs, and all other organs. Some stem cells remain active into adulthood and throughout an individual's life. These adult stem cells continuously produce intermediate cells called transient amplifying cells which become replacement bone, blood, and skin cells. But biologically speaking, it would be much less complex, and less expensive in terms of energy, if replacement cells were produced directly from other skin or fat cells by simple cell division instead of through levels of intermediate amplifying cells. Yet, this is not the case. So why then are so many cells replaced by this much less efficient method?
			<br /><br />John Pepper of the University of Arizona has recently put forward the surprising explanation that adult stem cells exist in long-lived animals and humans for the purpose of preventing evolution from happening. 2 Evolution, that is, within a single individual. An individual can be thought of as a group of cooperating cells. Every time a cell divides, there is an opportunity for genetic errors or mutations to occur (micro-evolution). If skin cells were replaced by division of existing skin cells, there would be billions of opportunities for mutations to occur which could lead to cancer. By contrast, cell replacement using amplified stem cells always starts out with a non-mutated cell which is amplified only a limited number of times. This method prevents the accumulation of harmful mutations. If this were not the case, as people age, their organs would be at risk of breaking down because of the accumulation of mutated cells.
			<br /><br />This finding that adult stem cells are needed to prevent evolution within an individual has striking implications. The unexpected choice of amplified stem cell replacement over direct cell division replacement speaks of purpose by deliberate design. But rather than recognize this, Dr. Pepper suggests that millions of years ago, single-celled animals could never have evolved into stable multicellular animals until the mechanism that stops evolution from occurring had also evolved. Is he really saying that for multicellular evolution to have occurred at all there must first have evolved a way to stop evolution? Don't you think this is asking quite a lot of an evolutionary process which cannot think ahead?
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 J. Panno, Stem Cell Research: Medical applications and ethical controversy (New York, NY: Facts on File, Inc., 2005).
			<br />2 J.W. Pepper, et al., Animal Cell Differentiation Patterns Suppress Somatic Evolution, Plos Computational Biology. Vol 3(12) e250; 2532-2545, 2007.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="bearing-strangers">
		<title>Bearing Strangers</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Xenophora_web.jpg" />
			<em>Exceptional evidence</em>
			<br /><br />In science, the exception is often more interesting and informative than the rule. And if these cases are examined through eyes of faith, one may also see evidence of God's knowledge and power on display. One such exception is found in the unique camouflage of the marine "carrier-shell" mollusk. Camouflage is a form of visual deception using color and pattern. Hunters wear "camo" clothing to blend into the surrounding environment. Animal camouflage is based on the same principle as that used by hunters, except that animals generally do not choose their camouflage. Instead, hair color and patterns are genetically inherited, although they may change with age or season of the year. For example, a white-tailed deer fawn is reddish brown with white spots at birth. This cryptic coloration is so effective that a doe can leave her fawn hidden in the grass for hours while she feeds. The spots later fade away about the time the fawn is weaned.
			<br /><br />An exception to the rule of inherited camouflage is the family of Xenophoridae mollusks that live in the tropical water of the western Pacific.1 Mollusks are soft-bodied animals without an internal skeleton. Some, like snails and clams, live in protective shells while others, like octopus and squid, do not. Xenophora (Greek for "bearer of strangers") mollusks are called "carrier-shell" mollusks because the animal deliberately picks up empty shells, fragments of shells, or small rocks and cements them to its own shell. Using its muscular foot, this mollusk can take up to 1.5 hours to select, clean, rotate, and fit an object onto the shell. Actual cementing may take up to ten hours! While this process makes the shell stronger, it is also effective camouflage against predators.
			<br /><br />Exceptional as this behavior is, it is even more incredible because the animal under the shell is essentially blind. While it may have some light sensitive pigment spots, they cannot form an image. Does this blind mollusk really know that other animals use their vision to hunt for it and, in response, camouflage its shell to avoid being seen? Probably not. Xenophora does not have a large brain so the camouflage behaviors are likely pre-programmed instinctive actions.
			<br /><br />"Bearing strangers" as camouflage does help Xenophora survive. But does this camouflage reveal more than it conceals? Perhaps this particular exception to the rule of inherited camouflage reveals the presence and power of a divine Designer who understands what Xenophora does not. Exceptions like Xenophora are hard to explain by sequential steps of natural selection since the behaviors of choosing, cleaning, rotating, and cementing are all needed simultaneously to create the camouflage. And if these behaviors have survival value, why do no other mollusk families exhibit these same behaviors? By contrast, a divine Designer would understand the survival value of camouflage for a blind animal hiding under a shell. An exception to the rule, yes, but also one in which we see the knowledge and power of the Creator on display before our eyes.
			<br /><br />- Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 J. L. Douglass, John Douglass (illustrated by), Roger Tory Peterson (series editor), Peterson First Guide to Shells of North American (Boston, MA: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1998).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="denial-to-discovery">
		<title>Denial to Discovery</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/AntonyFlew_headshot_SM.jpg" />
			<em>Atheism yields to reason</em>
			<br /><br />It was a long journey from denial to discovery, but the journey isn't over yet. After seventy years of following where the evidence led, prominent atheist philosopher Antony Flew announced in 2004 that he had finally "discovered God." The announcement rocked the world of fundamentalist atheism to its core. Now, in his 2007 book, There is a God: how the world's most notorious atheist changed his mind1, Professor Flew more completely outlines the evidence and arguments that led him to repudiate atheism.
			<br /><br />The scientific arguments supporting God's existence presented by Flew are strikingly familiar to anyone who has followed the creation/evolution/intelligent design controversy over the last twenty-five years. He observes first that nature obeys discoverable laws that are mathematical in form and are finely tuned in degree. Secondly, it surprised Dr. Flew to discover that the chemistry of life, the DNA molecule for example, is intelligently organized and that life is purpose-driven. Lastly, he realized that the universe is not eternal but had a beginning and so it was caused to exist by something outside the universe. His was a pilgrimage, not of faith, but of reason, and, at long last, he "discovered" an infinite, intelligent "Mind" (a.k.a. "God") behind the observable universe.
			<br /><br />But why should it take Flew so long to come to a conclusion that many scientists see as obvious or even self-evident - that design and purpose in the universe originate in a transcendent, infinite God who really does exist? Flew admits to being largely unaware of the progress made by science since he published the conclusions of his earliest work in philosophy. Those conclusions became the mold which shaped how he interpreted all later evidence bearing on the reality of God. In other words, his a priori assumption of atheism prevented him from seeing where the scientific evidence actually led. He paints this error as "the peculiar danger, the endemic evil, of dogmatic atheism." These are shockingly strong words from the former atheist and a candid admission of a lifetime of error.
			<br /><br />Aldous Huxley, the troubled English essayist, once observed that "[t]he course of every intellectual if he pursues his journey long and unflinchingly enough, ends in the obvious, from which the non-intellectuals have never stirred." This describes Flew's intellectual journey well but fails to take into account the many people he has led into the error of atheism during his life. This is an unenviable record that he may one day be called to account for. And his journey is not over because, although he now believes God exists, he does not yet know the God of the Bible personally, and Flew does not "think of [himself] as surviving death." So, what good is it to gain the whole world but lose your own soul? What is needed by Flew, now 84, and all who are still in denial, is not just a change of mind, but a change of destiny, and this only happens when, as Jesus says, you are "born again" (Jn. 3:3).
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 Antony Flew and R.A. Varghese, There is a God: How the world's most notorious atheist changed his mind (New York, NY: HarperCollins Publishers, 2007).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="in-the-beginning">
		<title>In the Beginning</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/LynxArc.jpg" />
			<em>Ask One who was there</em>
			<br /><br />Francis Schaeffer begins his book on the rise and decline of modern Western thought and culture by considering ancient Rome and the Greek influences on its culture and thinking.1 Among these were the 4th century B.C. writings of the Greek philosopher Aristotle who believed that the earth was at the center of a universe made of concentric crystalline spheres. He also believed that the universe was eternal and uncreated, a concept later disputed by Christian and Jewish philosophers because of the first three words of Genesis: "In the beginning&hellip;"
			<br /><br />For a thousand years after the birth, death, and resurrection of Christ, Christian, Jewish, and even Muslim scholars argued from logic and mathematics that the universe was not eternal but, in fact, had a beginning and that beginning was proof that a transcendent Creator God existed. The argument from logic can be stated as follows: Whatever begins to exist has a cause that brings it into being, and, since the universe began to exist, the universe is therefore not eternal but had a cause outside of itself.2 But those who accepted the testimony of the book of Genesis had known for a thousand years before Aristotle that the universe had both a beginning and a Beginner. Ironically, the Christian philosopher Thomas Aquinas, in the 13th century A.D., accepted Aristotle's view of an eternal universe even as he sought to prove the existence of God based, in part, on the need for a "first efficient cause."
			<br /><br />The belief that matter, energy, and the universe were uncreated persisted through the development of modern science and on into the early 20th century. But by then both theory and observational evidence suggested the universe had a definite beginning. For example, William Thomson (Lord Kelvin) and others developed the First and Second Laws of Thermodynamics, which state that matter and energy cannot be created or destroyed (the First Law) but only changed in quality (the Second Law) by energy becoming less useful for mechanical and biological work (increased entropy).
			<br /><br />Together, these two laws predict the universe had a beginning at some point in time past, when all energy was useful energy. What they do not explain is where the energy came from originally. In 1929, astronomer Edwin Hubble observed light from distant stars was "red-shifted." This suggested they were moving away from us and the universe was expanding. We are told that such an expansion or explosion would have started from an infinitely dense, hot kernel at some time in the past. But where did the kernel come from?
			<br /><br />Today, almost one hundred years later, the weight of theory and observation has produced a cautious, uneasy acceptance by many scientists that the universe is not eternal but did have a beginning. They are uneasy because if the 3500-year-old biblical statement "In the beginning&hellip;" was correct long before science came to the conclusion of a beginning, then perhaps the next phrase - "God created" - requires their attention as well.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 F.A. Schaeffer, How Should We Then Live? (Wheaton, IL: Crossway Books, 1996).
			<br />2 W. L. Craig, God, Are You There? (Norcross, GA: Ravi Zacharias International Ministries, 1999).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="forensic-universe">
		<title>Forensic Universe</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/ForensicUniverse.jpg" />
			<em>A cosmic whodunit</em>
			<br /><br />The Hardy Boys mystery books were a favorite of mine in my pre-teen years. By close observation and deductive reasoning from fragmented facts, Joe and Frank always solved the mystery and caught the bad guy. Their real life equivalents are forensic pathologists who analyze blood, hair, or fiber evidence from a crime scene which, when combined with other forms of evidence, can help identify the perpetrator. Detectives may also develop a partial profile of the personality and abilities of the suspect based on the information gathered from the scene. But is it possible to apply forensic reasoning to the universe as a whole? If there is a "Someone" responsible for the way the universe is, could we develop a partial profile of this Someone from our basic understanding of the universe? Engineer and inventor David Penny has suggested that, indeed, we can develop a profile of the Creator from what has been created.1 Penny suggests that key observations about the universe in general, and human beings in particular, indicate that the agent responsible for creation must have had at least four characteristics. That is, the Creator would be personal, powerful, intelligent, and non-material (i.e. spiritual).
			<br /><br />Every engineer, painter, or sculptor is at least as complex as the most complicated part of whatever they create. So, firstly, the Creator would be a person and have insight, reasoning, and emotions as do the most complex of living things: human beings. Secondly, the Creator would have access to, and control over, all the energy needed to start the universe in the beginning. Consider that when you wind up a rubber band-powered airplane, you actually transfer your energy to the rubber band. From the point when the plane is released, the energy in the rubber band is converted into the spinning of the propeller and the energy is spent. So, too, the universe started with a set amount of energy imparted to it by the Creator and has been running down ever since. Thirdly, the Creator would have the intelligence to create consistent physical laws that govern the interactions of matter, as well as the intelligence to design and build complex biochemical motors and living systems. And, fourthly, to accomplish all this, the Creator would need access to all parts of the very large universe simultaneously and therefore could not be made of matter as He would need to travel faster than the speed of light. Nor could a Creator made of matter survive the intense temperatures some predict were present at the moment of creation. So, whether the universe was large or small, the agent of creation could not have been made of physical matter.
			<br /><br /><br />What we leave behind always reveals something about us. But it can also be incomplete. The same is true of the forensic universe. It reveals in part the transcendent, powerful, personal God of creation. But it is the further revelation in the Bible of the death of Jesus Christ on the cross that more completely reveals His love for each of us.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 David Penny, Scientific Implications About Origins, www.gravitationalrelativity.com
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="fish-food">
		<title>Fish Food</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/cookedFish_web.jpg" />
			<em>Beware the Cartoon Diet.</em>
			<br /><br />There are often news stories promoting causes like animal rights, whaling bans, or vegetarian diets. The tone of these reports attempts to place advocates of these issues on a higher moral and ethical plain than those who believe that both plants and animals have been given to people as food. But using plants and animals for food isn't only supported by the Bible (Gen. 1:29; 9:3), but by biology as well.
			<br /><br />The biological truth is that all animals live off the death of other living things, be they plants (herbivores) or other animals (carnivores). Death is essential for life because death provides the building blocks and fuel for life. Unlike the Disney version of nature, where animals speak English and eat only fruits and nuts, real animals routinely kill and eat each other just as they are designed to do. And whether they are a cat or a shark, they kill without any ethical or moral anxiety over the rights of their prey. This was sharply illustrated when I watched our pet cat catch, kill, and devour a wild rabbit, something he does instinctively and regularly.
			<br /><br />Evolutionists typically view people as just another type of animal. Oddly, some of them also believe it is ethically and morally wrong for people to kill and eat animals when this same practice is essential for the survival of all animals on earth. In its place, some suggest that people eat only vegetables and grains - as if this practice does not involve the death of a living organism.
			<br /><br />It is possible to live a healthy life on a vegetarian diet. However, one must be careful to eat the right combination of vegetables because particular vegetables lack some of the amino acids people need. By contrast, red meat and fish are the richest, most complete individual sources of all essential amino acids in the human diet.
			<br /><br />Fish are a particularly healthy dietary choice because so-called "oily" fish like tuna, sardines, salmon, mackerel, and herring contain an abundance of polyunsaturated fats called Omega-3 fats. The American Heart Association currently recommends eating oily fish at least twice a week for the prevention of heart disease.1
			<br /><br />Despite the health benefits of eating fish, Disney continues to promote a fictitious view of nature. In the animated film Finding Nemo, Bruce is a great white shark with a "problem" - he eats other fish for food. To change this unacceptable behavior he attends a self-help group with two other sharks. Together they repeat the mantra "fish are friends, not food" and support each other on the seven-step road to recovery. But real sharks are designed to eat other fish, and one wonders what Bruce would eat if he did not eat fish.
			<br /><br />While humans are not animals, human life is dependent on the death of plants and animals for survival and this is consistent with both biology and the Bible. So we - and Bruce - can eat up with a clear conscience because fish really are food, not friends.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 W.S. Harris, "Fish oil supplementation: Evidence for health benefits," Cleveland Clinic Journal of Medicine, vol. 71(3), 2004, 208-221.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="spiritual-signs-and-symptoms">
		<title>Spiritual Signs and Symptoms</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/doctorSeriousScrubs.jpg" />
			<em>What can sickness teach us?</em>
			<br /><br />Babies cry because they cannot say what is wrong or where it hurts. Crying is thus a visible and audible symptom of an underlying problem. Hunger or wetness can be dealt with easily, but, if crying continues, parents become medical detectives, looking for other general symptoms that may indicate an infection or disease. For example, a runny nose or pain in the muscles or joints are some common, qualitative symptoms that could point to either bacterial or viral infection. The diagnosis based on symptoms is confirmed by the results of specific tests that are medically called signs. In this case, the child's body temperature could be elevated, a blood test could reveal increased numbers of bacteria-eating, white-blood cells, or ear fluid could be used to grow and identify disease-causing bacteria. Signs and symptoms like those above lead to the realization that a disease or infection is actively hurting the body and needs to be treated. They are a call to action.
			<br /><br />This is not to say that the body cannot actively defend itself. In fact, the symptoms of redness and swelling at the site of a cut indicate the body is doing just that, bringing bacteria-eating white blood cells to the area. Likewise, most viral infections resolve after seven to ten days because the body produces its own anti-viral medicine called interferon. To the knowledgeable observer, it seems that the human body's active defenses against bacteria and viruses must have been designed with foreknowledge of what they would be fighting. But if these lines of defense fail and the infection or disease continues without treatment, there can be severe consequences. Hearing or sight can be lost. Limbs may need to be amputated. Damage to the heart or other organs can occur. Some infections, like pneumonia, can result in death, as is frequently the case among elderly people in nursing homes. To ignore the call to action of ongoing signs and symptoms can have terrible, even deadly, results.
			<br /><br />Just as in the physical realm, spiritual signs and symptoms serve to call attention to the reality of an underlying spiritual problem that, if left untreated, results in death. An observer of human history would note the general, but chronic, symptoms of selfishness, hate, violence, and moral ambiguity, and the ensuing specific signs of innumerable wars, the killing of millions of unborn children, and the legal redefinition of sexuality and gender, as confirmation of an underlying spiritual disease. The disease is called sin. Sin is a congenital spiritual disease of human beings that keeps us separated from God and, if left untreated, is eternally fatal. Spiritual signs and symptoms call for an effective spiritual prescription.
			<br /><br />Thankfully, there is an effective treatment freely available. Like a physician prescribing the right medicine to cure an infection, the biblical prescription for the disease of sin is faith in Jesus Christ. Only faith in Jesus brings relief from the symptoms of sin, an eternal resolution of the infection of sin, and freedom from the fatal outcome of sin.
			<br /><br />"But He was pierced through for our transgressions, He was crushed for our iniquities; the chastening for our well-being fell upon Him, and by His scourging we are healed" (Isa. 53:5).
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="wise-man">
		<title>Wise Man?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/ThinkingGuy_web.jpg" />
			<em>We may be giving ourselves too much credit.</em>
			<br /><br />In 1735, the Swiss botanist Carl Linnaeus proposed an ingenious, shorthand way to name plants using one Latin word to designate the "genus" group and another to identify a particular "species" within that genus. Used together, the terms make up the unique "binomial" name of each plant species. The system has since been expanded to include bacteria, animals, and human beings. The two-word designation for humans is Homo sapiens, which literally means wise or knowing man. But have we named ourselves wisely? Surely we know a lot of information and we are intelligent, but is intelligence the same as wisdom?
			<br /><br />The Eastern Gray Squirrel (Sciurus carolinensis) cannot pass a standard intelligence test but is often used as an object lesson of "wise" behavior because it stockpiles nuts in advance of winter when its food becomes scarce. The American Black Bear (Ursus americanus) is not a Rhodes Scholar, but it wisely prepares for winter by eating voraciously in the summer and fall, accumulating enough fat to sustain itself during its long winter hibernation. The female black bear breeds in the spring but delays development of the embryo until after beginning her winter hibernation, by which time she has put on enough fat to sustain both herself and her growing embryo.
			<br /><br />To some extent wisdom includes the ability to act in the present to preserve the future good. But, like the examples above, much of animal behavior is unlearned and instinctive. It is this pre-programmed behavior we view as "wise." By contrast, human beings, though highly intelligent, are not pre-programmed and so must learn wisdom by experience, insight, reflection, or even by revelation. One writer wryly observed that wisdom and good judgment come from experience, but experience comes from poor judgment. One might reasonably conclude from this that animals are wise but unintelligent; whereas, humans are intelligent but often unwise.
			<br /><br />So, does "Wise Man" live up to the name? Do we use our intelligence wisely by planning now to supply future needs? Unfortunately, the answer seems to be no. Examples of intelligent people making unwise decisions abound. A recent Frontline episode suggested that most people do not plan for retirement, even though they know there is a time coming when they will be unable to work. Far more tragically, most people do not plan for their spiritual futures either. Choosing to ignore rather than accept God's present offer of salvation through Jesus Christ is the very antithesis of wisdom. It is foolishness on an eternal scale.
			<br /><br /><br />Bruce Sterling, imagining the future extinction of "Wise Man" in the year 2380 and writing as a non-human news reporter in the journal Nature, suggests the following epitaph on the fictional passing of Homo sapiens: "They were very, very curious but not at all far-sighted."1 Thankfully, this needn't describe believers. As Jim Elliot, the martyred missionary to the Auca Indians, wisely wrote in his diary, "He is no fool who gives what he cannot keep to gain that which he cannot lose."
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 B. Sterling, "Homo sapiens declared extinct," Nature, vol. 402, 1999, 125.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-world-as-we-know-it">
		<title>The World as We Know It</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/WeGoBeach.jpg" />
			The Hawaiian Islands are volcanic in origin. Molten lava from deep below the ocean floor escaped into the cool Pacific waters and hardened into mountains, only the tops of which break the surface and appear to us as islands. Occasional volcanic eruptions spill hot lava down the mountainside, threatening everything in its path with incineration. The lava eventually cools and hardens, becoming a dark rock of jagged shapes. Along the coastal highway appear patterns of white rocks against the black lava. These are actually chunks of coral skeletons made of white calcium carbonate that have been arranged into letters and words. Some send birthday wishes and some exalt the most recent senior class. One formation simply says, "WE GO BEACH."
			<br /><br />Could these patterns and words be caused by waves randomly tossing coral chunks onto the lava? We quickly dismiss this as nonsense. Still, we are invited by evolutionary theory to believe that matter has the natural tendency to self-assemble into living machines much more complex than coral words. And that structures such as the feathers and hollow bones needed for birds to have arisen from reptiles were not intentionally designed but are the result of undirected chance and natural selection. Intelligent design theorist William Dembski has developed a three step method, or algorithm, to determine whether a given pattern exists by necessity, chance, or by deliberate design.1 He calls the "characteristic trademark or signature" of intelligence, "specified complexity." To be considered the result of intelligent action a pattern must first be rare - one of many possible choices of patterns; then complex - improbable; and finally, specified - following independent rules like those of English grammar.
			<br /><br />We are sure the coral words on the lava did not form by chance because they are rare, complex, and specified. A similar application of Dembski's method to the biological world makes it difficult to support a non-intelligent source for all of life. Yet this is exactly what standard evolutionary theory asserts. Here, then, is one of the core problems many people have with the whole idea of evolution: it simply does not fit the reality of the world as we know it. Intentional dog or orchid breeding has never resulted in a dog becoming a reptile or an orchid becoming an oak tree. That is, even deliberate, selective, and intensive breeding cannot cross the boundaries between genetic types. How then could undirected chance accomplish this so easily and so often?
			<br /><br />Today we see life coming only from pre-existing life rather than coming spontaneously from non-life. Like coral words on lava, living things show the marks of having been designed. Intelligent choices appear to have been made between competing biological design options. Complex biological structures are used where they are needed. And levels of organization, integration, and regulation exist between cells, organs, and organisms that seem to be imposed on them. Life is specified complexity and specified complexity, like the coral words "WE GO BEACH," does not happen by chance.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 M. Behe, W. Dembski, S. Meyer, Proceedings of the Wethersfield Institute, vol. 9, Science and Evidence for Design in the Universe (San Francisco, CA: Ignatius Press, 2000).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="unseen-reality">
		<title>Unseen Reality</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/MagneticField.jpg" />
			<em>We're surrounded by the invisible.</em>
			<br /><br />Not everything that is real can be seen. My five year-old son and I enjoy making geometric shapes using magnets molded into plastic rods which then cling to small steel balls. Bringing the magnet close to the ball causes the ball to be drawn toward, and held to, the magnet. The force that causes the ball to move is real, but invisible. Magnetic fields can occur naturally or be generated by electric currents. They can be measured and manipulated, but they are invisible to human eyes. Instead, what can be seen or felt are the effects of magnetic fields on objects like steel balls, iron filings, or even other magnets. The effect is called a "force" because one can feel the pulling together or the pushing apart of two magnets, depending on how they are oriented, when held close together.
			<br /><br />Other examples of unseen reality and its effects abound. For centuries the causes of disease were not known, in part because viruses and bacteria could not be seen. Though invisible to the unaided eye, the effect of the plague bacterium was deadly. Called the Black Death, it killed 30 million peasants in 14th century Europe. In the 16th and 17th centuries, the all but invisible smallpox and influenza viruses swept through the New World with devastating effects, killing an estimated 100 million people in what one historian called "the Great Dying"1. We cannot see moving air, or the nitrogen, oxygen, and carbon dioxide molecules that are part of air, but its effect is called wind. We see light of different wavelengths or colors, but most of the electromagnetic spectrum from gamma rays to x-rays, ultraviolet, infrared, radar and radio/TV waves are invisible to humans. Even so, the effects of these energy waves are very real. For example, x-rays are used for medical diagnosis, ultraviolet light fuels the production of Vitamin D in human skin, and modern aircraft and ships navigate and communicate using radar and shortwave signals.
			<br /><br />If we believe so often in things that are unseen because we see their effects, isn't it also reasonable to believe in a God who, though He cannot be seen, has shown us His reality by the effects He has in the universe, in history, and in the lives of real people? Some have come to believe that only what can be measured by gauges, instruments, and detectors is real. But this is true poverty of the spirit because what then becomes of the reality of love, of beauty, and of faith?
			<br /><br />Magnetic fields can be made visible by iron filings on a sheet of paper. Wind that takes up smoke or debris becomes visible. Special glasses detect infrared heat sources and television signals become images on a screen. Unseen reality can be made visible. Such is the miracle of the incarnation: the unseen, but real, God making Himself visible in the person of a baby. And the name of this "effect" is Jesus.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 A. Nikiforuk, The Fourth Horseman: A short history of epidemics, plagues, famines and other scourges (New York, NY: M. Evans &amp; Co., 1991).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-grand-illusion">
		<title>The Grand Illusion</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/FeatherBlue.jpg" />
			<em>Once The Truth is rejected, all other truth is fair game.</em>
			<br /><br />I hate gravity. Oh, it has its uses, like keeping my morning coffee in the cup and holding down all the files of scientific articles stacked up in my office. But it also consistently causes me unnecessary aggravation. I open the freezer door and the ice cream slips out and heads toward my toes. If I stand two rolling suitcase bags next to each other, one will invariably fall and knock the other over. When I bend over to pick up the bags, my glasses fall on the floor. If I pile up my collection of CDs, they will not be in a neat stack when I return.
			<br /><br />Gravity does not discriminate, nor does it take vacations. It is relentless. Gravity is an opportunistic predator that takes advantage of small deviations from level to bring any object down to the lowest level of potential energy - usually the floor. Most adults courageously fight the good fight against gravity every day. Teenagers, on the other hand, have not yet taken up the struggle and live in relative harmony with gravity - especially in their bedrooms. Everything just automatically goes on the floor, giving gravity nothing more to do.
			<br /><br />Perhaps teenagers intuitively sense something that some theoretical physicists are now considering: could gravity really be just a grand illusion? In a recent Scientific American article, former Harvard University physicist Juan Maldacena says one of the three dimensions of space - height, width, or length - might be an illusion created by particles moving in just two dimensions, and that gravity, too, "would be part of the illusion." 1 Maldacena uses the example of a holographic image which appears to be three-dimensional, even though it is physically a two-dimensional object. In a holographic image, depth is an illusion.
			<br /><br />Illusions are fine in holographs and the world of the theoretical physicist, but we live in a world where gravity and its effects are very real. For decades there has been a growing gap between science based on observable, repeatable events and experiments, and the non-testable theories of virtual universes and dimensions of the theoretical physicist. Without the requirement for experimental verification, speculation and theory too often become fact by simple assertion. For example, Maldacena asserts that, in the quantum view of the world, everything is in flux. Even so-called empty space, "which is, in fact, filled with virtual particles that perpetually pop in and out of existence," is not really empty.1 Theoretical physicists have come to accept theory as fact and have, in turn, encouraged the general public to regard verifiable facts as a grand illusion. As much as I might wish gravity were an illusion, I am not persuaded to believe that it is so by pseudo-scientific assertions of what "might" be based on quantum physics. No, the evidence that gravity is not an illusion is too easily found in my teenager's room, where I can't see, let alone walk on, the bedroom floor.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 J. Maldacena, "The Illusion of Gravity," Scientific American, November 2005, 56-63.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-wonderful-net">
		<title>The Wonderful Net</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/HeronSilhouette.jpg" />
			<em>Freak chance or deliberate design?</em>
			<br /><br />Swimsuit-clad men, determined to qualify as U.S. Navy Seals, sit in the cool ocean water off Coronado Island near San Diego, California. Their body temperature gets lower and lower until they become hypothermic and incoherent after just a few hours in the water. Nearby, shorebirds such as the heron, stand motionless in the same water yet their body temperature does not fall. How can this be so? The answer is that herons, but not human beings, employ a principle called "counter-current exchange" to conserve heat that would otherwise be lost to the ocean water. P. F. Scholander has called the counter-current exchanger "the wonderful net" and characterizes it as "a truly remarkable piece of biological engineering." 1
			<br /><br />Heat flows from warmer to cooler areas. Moving the areas in opposite, or counter, directions makes heat flow between the two areas much more efficient. In the heron, warm blood flows down out of the bird's trunk and into its legs through arteries that are closely interwoven with a network of veins coming up from the legs, carrying cool blood in the opposite direction. Heat from the arterial blood quickly moves into the cold, venous blood. This warms the blood coming into the bird's main body and cools the blood going out. Along with an insulating layer of feathers, this wonderful net of blood vessels keeps the heron from becoming hypothermic. People have a similar counter-current exchanger in the kidneys to regulate salt and water balance, but do not use counter-current nets of blood vessels to reduce heat loss to the environment. Instead, the human body restricts blood flow to the skin, reduces blood flow into arms and legs, and generates heat by shivering.
			<br /><br />Counter-current exchangers are also found in some land animals like the armadillo, the sloth, and the anteater, which are very sensitive to low temperatures, but not in other animals like the fox or the Husky sled dog. Some shorebirds, like herons and cranes, have counter-current nets while other waterfowl, like ducks, geese, and gulls, do not. It seems that ducks and geese have a need, not to conserve, but to lose body heat because of their very efficient body insulation.
			<br /><br />Scholander concedes that counter-current exchangers appear to be designed, or engineered, solutions to the specific physiological challenges faced by some animals but not others. They are found in animals as diverse as the tuna, the seal, the squirrel, and the heron but not in other types of birds or land animals. In other words, they are used selectively and intelligently on an "as needed" basis. Evolution proponents call this "convergent" evolution - where unrelated animal groups independently evolve the same solution to a common problem. This is interesting speculation, but naming something does not explain, nor prove, how it came to be. By contrast, we could reasonably infer that this "truly remarkable piece of biological engineering" came from the hand of the truly remarkable Creator who used the appropriate design elements, where needed, for each type of animal and for people.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 P.F. Scholander, "The Wonderful Net," in Vertebrate Structures and Functions: Readings from Scientific American (San Francisco, CA: W.H. Freeman and Company, 1969), pp.125-131.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-power-of-prediction">
		<title>The Power of Prediction</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/BigCrowdStairs.jpg" />
			<em>What can you really trust in for the future?</em>
			<br /><br />Predictions have power. They influence emotions, alter behavior, and even change social policies. During the 1960's, it was predicted that the earth would become overpopulated within a few generations. It seemed there would be no end to the periodic doubling of the human population and the negative environmental impact this would bring. Rachel Carson's 1962 book, Silent Spring, predicted a future springtime without the familiar songs of wild birds1. She based this prediction on the widespread use of the pesticide DDT to control mosquitoes in populated areas, and the discovery that DDT made songbird eggs so fragile that many were crushed in the nest. Carson predicted that if population growth and DDT use continued, then fewer birds would be born each spring - until one spring when there would be only silence. Her prediction ignited a new environmental movement in the United States that spearheaded a successful campaign to ban the use of DDT.
			<br /><br />The fear of overpopulation has influenced personal choices and public policy decisions for generations. Part of the power of the "population explosion" prediction is due to the ability of the average person to understand its mathematical basis. If the time that was needed for a population to double is known, this can be used to project future growth. The numbers grow slowly at first but then suddenly rise explosively, or geometrically, and reach toward infinity. One 1970's-era astronomy textbook used this geometric progression to predict the earth's population would become infinite on Friday the 13th of November, 20262. A day they called "doomsday." Doomsday predictions abound in the secular media today. The earth might be annihilated at any moment by a meteor impact. Human life may succumb to bird flu or some antibiotic-resistant plague. A giant volcanic eruption could plunge the world into an ice age. Conversely, fossil fuel use might cause global warming, resulting in coastal flooding around the world.
			<br /><br />So far, all these predictions have been wrong. Even the predictions of overpopulation may be wrong. Author Phillip Longman, in his recent book, The Empty Cradle, contends that birth rates in many cultures are well below replacement levels3. Longman suggests our current 6 billion- person population may never actually double but only increase to 9 billion by 2070 and then begin to decrease! This, he predicts, would cause social and economic problems for future generations. After all, nothing can replace the babies who were never born because they were aborted, or because women entered the workforce and chose to have fewer children.
			<br /><br />So are we headed for environmental ruin from overpopulation or economic collapse from under population? This exposes one problem with predictions: they can't be validated until after they come to pass. Christians are often scolded by the secular world for expecting the return of Jesus Christ at any moment based on biblical predictions (prophesies). But the lesson from secular history is that while man's predictions do have power, they can also be wrong. The lesson from biblical history is that only God's predictions can be relied on to surely come to pass.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes:
			<br /><br />1 R. Carson, Silent Spring, (New York, NY: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1962).
			<br />2 G.O. Abell, Exploration of the Universe, (New York, NY: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1974).
			<br />3 P. Longman, The Empty Cradle: How falling birthrates threaten world prosperity, (New York, NY: Basic Books, 2004).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="surprised-by-design">
		<title>Surprised by Design</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/MicroscopeFace.jpg" />
			<em>Is it rational to think that the greatest design of all is merely an accident?</em>
			<br /><br />During World War II and the Cold War which followed, Soviet Russia was well known for its skill in "reverse engineering." That is, they were able to take apart and analyze captured enemy equipment and incorporate into their own weapons any innovations in design and performance made by enemy scientists and engineers. For example, the Russian Tupolev Tu-4 heavy bomber looked strikingly like the American B-29 bomber, and with good reason: it was patterned almost bolt by bolt after three captured B-29 aircraft which landed in Russian territory in 1945.
			<br /><br />Another, less successful, example of reverse engineering was the Russian space shuttle called "Buran," Russian for "snowstorm." Its external dimensions and design are essentially identical to the United States space shuttle called STS for "space transportation system." But without access to an intact STS shuttle to copy, the Russians were unable to produce a completed shuttle, and the Buran never flew with a human crew aboard.
			<br /><br />Closer to home, I recently purchased a set of shelves for my office and liked them so much that I wanted to make an additional set via reverse engineering. So, using the completed shelves as a pattern, I carefully measured the sides, cross pieces, top and bottom, etc. When I looked at these measurements to determine how much wood was required for the shelves and how they might be cut most efficiently, I suddenly realized that the basic structural components of the shelves were designed to be cut out of a single piece of 4-foot by 8-foot oak laminated plywood. This is a standard, mass produced plywood that is less expensive than solid oak but very strong due to the lamination. Suddenly, I found myself thinking the thoughts of the shelves' designers after they had, simply by dissecting the finished product of their design. I knew that questions of efficient supply of raw materials, minimization of waste, structural strength, and aesthetics were all answered by the intentional design of the shelves before me.
			<br /><br />Biological scientists have always used, and still use, the process of reverse engineering, except that the objects analyzed are living things. The scientific method itself is really one of reverse engineering of a completed product - life. During the 1950's, James Watson and Francis Crick started with purified DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid), a finished product, and were able to deduce its helical structure from X-ray diffraction patterns. This was soon followed by an appreciation of how DNA and other molecules were used to store, duplicate, and express biological information in a living cell.
			<br /><br />These biological principles, derived from reverse engineering, are universally taught in schools today. But this familiarity should not dampen our sense of wonder and surprise at our ability to think the thoughts of God after Him. Scientists expect there to be understandable reasons for why the living world is the way it is. It is precisely this human expectation of being able to rationally determine how living things work that is the telltale evidence of the Creator God.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="which-forever-is-coming">
		<title>Which Forever is Coming?</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/FutureLightBlurs.jpg" />
			<em>It's a good idea to think about forever before you get there.</em>
			<br /><br />Forever is coming, whether we like it or not. The question is: which forever? Physicists and astronomers proclaim they know how and when the universe began and approximately when and how it will end. In the book, Endless Universe, the authors begin the story of the universe with the words: "From nothing" and "from nowhere" a "tiny speck of brilliant light appeared" and began to expand "not into anything, but throughout, because the Universe was, and is, everything and everywhere"1. There was no particular reason for the appearance of the speck some 13 billion years ago, they explain. It just happened. They then fast forward 8.4 billion years to when our sun and solar system, including earth, have formed. Add another billion years and the first life has appeared on earth. This would be, they say, about 3.5 billion years before the present.
			<br /><br />But how long will life survive on earth, and what is the ultimate "forever" for each person and the universe as a whole? The Christian and the Materialist answer these questions very differently. The Materialist sees life as a short-lived accident in the long history of the universe. One author estimates we have two billion years before life on earth becomes extinct. By that time, we are told, our sun will expand to become a red giant star and burn or melt the earth to a lifeless lump of rock. This would make the entire history of life on earth about 5.5 billion years long. Five billion (5 x 109) years of life in a universe spanning 1 x 10100 years is less than a blink of an eye. So life is seen as a brief accident. It came from nowhere, has no meaning or purpose, and as quickly as it arose, it will be gone.
			<br /><br />But God has revealed in the Bible a distinctly different account of the origin and future of life; one that shows there is a reason for, and a purpose in, life and human existence. The purposeful order, complexity, and rationality of living things, as well as the elegant mathematical structure of the universe, are a reflection of the One who made all things by the Word of His power. They are the forensic evidence of the Creator (Rom. 1:20).
			<br /><br />The Materialist believes that in the far distant future our sun and all other stars will exhaust their fuel and become brown or white dwarf stars that then collapse into black holes to be destroyed. All matter will break down and the universe will cool to a temperature where nothing can ever happen again. The final forever, they predict, is cold, dark, and lifeless.
			<br /><br />The Christian agrees that forever is coming, but points out that the Bible teaches we must choose between two different forevers: one forever in God's presence and the other away from His presence. The evidence of the universe and of life clearly point us to God, not to chance, as the originator of life, and can also guide our choice of forevers.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote:
			<br /><br />1 H. Couper H and N. Henbest, Endless Universe. The Story of Space, Time, and the Search for Life Beyond Our Planet, (New York, NY: Covent Garden Press, 1999).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="small-may-be-big-but-it-isnt-new">
		<title>Small May Be Big, but It Isn't New</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/nanotech.jpg" />
			<em>The God of the infinite is the God of the infinitesimal</em>
			<br /><br />Small is big. Nanotechnology is the new marketing buzzword, with the Apple iPod Nano a case in point1. Going small is big business and has many potential applications, including targeting and treating cancer cells. Others see the potential to create smaller, more powerful computer chips2 or even human/machine hybrids. In his new book, Nano-Hype, David Beurube comments that nanotechnology is not really new but is the same old science on a smaller scale3. I agree but would go a step further and say God was into nanotechnology from the very beginning and that life was purposefully built on a series of biomechanical "nano-machines."
			<br /><br />One essential nano-machine is the water molecule. Water is composed of three atoms, two of hydrogen and one of oxygen, joined in the sequence H-O-H. Two sets of unpaired electrons on the oxygen atom force the molecule to bend to an obtuse angle of about 105 degrees. Bent in this way, one water molecule spans about three tenths of one nanometer in width. One nanometer is one billionth of a meter. This bending gives water a slight negative electrical charge on the oxygen end and a slight positive charge on the hydrogen end. It is this tiny separation between electric charges which makes life possible.
			<br /><br />Your body is 60% water by weight and almost all the space inside your cells not occupied by biological molecules (DNA, fats, and proteins) is filled with water. Water is the master electrical manager in living cells. The positive and negative ends of the water molecule give it the ability to form attachments with other water molecules and to cover charged parts of biological molecules with a water shell. The positively charged ends of fat molecules attract the negative ends of water molecules and the long, electrically neutral carbon chains in fat molecules repel water, preferring instead to group together. It is these forces of attraction and repulsion between water and fat that create the double-layered cell membrane of each of our 60 trillion cells and, without this membrane, there is no life.
			<br /><br />The nano-technology of water is also essential to our senses of taste and smell. To be tasted or smelled a substance must first be dissolved by water. Only then can it touch a receiving site on the olfactory cells of the nose or gustatory cells of the tongue. This tiny interaction outside the cell triggers a cascade, or series, of other nano-events inside the cell, causing a nerve impulse along the cell membrane. The impulse eventually reaches the brain which interprets it as sour, bitter, sweet, or salty.
			<br /><br />Water is but one example of a biomechanical nanomachine. Many, many others exist within us and the various plants and animals on earth. Each machine is finely tuned, organized, and integrated with multiple other machines to form a functional whole. This is a scale of miniaturization and purposeful, balanced complexity that could only come from the mind and hand of the Creator. Small may be big, but it is not new.
			<br /><br />Endnotes
			<br /><br />1 L Langdon, "Small Science," World (Mar. 4, 2006): pp. 32-34.
			<br />2 PJ Kuekes et al., "Crossbar Nanocomputers," Scientific American 293, no. 5 (Nov. 2005): pp. 72-80.
			<br />3 DM Beube, Nano-Hype (Prometheus Books, 2005).
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-miracle-and-mystery-of-life">
		<title>The Miracle and Mystery of Life</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/PlaneModel.jpg" />
			<em>The sum of the parts - without God - still doesn't equal life.</em>
			<br /><br />Modern aircraft can carry passengers and cargo to altitudes as high as six miles and are assembled from many thousands of precisely machined parts. The airplane as a whole can fly, even though it is made of non-flying parts. Take, for example, a wheel or a single wing flap or the fuselage. By themselves these parts cannot fly (throwing doesn't count), but when integrated with all the other parts, they take on a new characteristic that is not inherent in any of the individual parts - flight.
			<br /><br />It is not miraculous or mysterious that intelligent people discovered the mathematical and physical principles of flight and used them to build objects that fly. But it is miraculous and mysterious that life itself even exists, and that it exists in multiple levels of complexity. Life is really a compounded miracle. Take one cell from your mouth. This living cell is made of non-living chemicals like water, proteins, fats, acids, carbohydrates, and salts. These chemicals obey the laws of physics and chemistry based on their composition and can be separated or combined at will in a test tube. Yet they are not alive. So the property of life is not inherent within inorganic and organic chemicals. That is, life is not the result of spontaneous mixtures of dead chemicals as some of the evolutionary faith believe. Rather, the miracle of life is that dead chemicals were skillfully and intentionally arranged by someone into a form that they do not naturally take and which is far greater than the sum of the parts - a living cell.
			<br /><br />Compounding the miracle of life from dead chemicals are the levels of cooperation and specialization of cells that form organs, organ systems, whole organisms, and even populations of organisms like a flock of geese, a herd of sheep, or a forest ecosystem. These complex and interrelated systems are the compounded miracles of life. Within their boundaries they obey, but they do not create, the biological laws of genetic variation, natural selection, population dynamics, and biochemistry. Instead, these physical and biological laws must have been set in place by someone outside of the entire system. Someone we will call the Creator.
			<br /><br />So who is this mysterious Creator with the power and skill to form dead chemicals into living things? Many believe this question is unanswerable and is similar to the historical question of who built the ring of huge stone blocks in England called Stonehenge: people built Stonehenge but they did not leave their names inscribed on the stone nor are there written records identifying the builders. Likewise, the Creator did not inscribe His name on each strand of DNA or write it in the clouds for all to see. But, unlike the builders of Stonehenge, the Creator of the Universe wants to be known, and even worshiped. Since the living world around us is a compounded miracle, isn't it reasonable to start the search for the Creator by looking for Someone who performs miracles?
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="theres-no-place-like-home">
		<title>There's No Place Like Home</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Spacewalk.jpg" />
			Outer space is not a very inviting place to visit. There is no air or air pressure, no oxygen, no liquid water, no food, extremely high and low temperatures, and harmful radiation, to name a few features that don't match the basic requirements for life as we know it. We do visit space, but this requires intelligently engineered equipment to allow us to take our environment along with us. We must have oxygen-containing air at the correct pressure, otherwise blood would "boil" in the no-pressure vacuum of space. Food and water are essential, too, as is the right temperature for the biochemistry of life to run smoothly. And our DNA must be protected from damage by cosmic radiation. All of these conditions are already provided for us on earth. The physical conditions on earth exactly match the requirements to sustain human life with little or no effort on our part.Whereas it is with great effort that we take these conditions with us into space.
			<br /><br />Earth-like gravity is also difficult to take with us into space. The microgravity environment of space looks like fun, but microgravity is actually harmful to humans. In the short term, with no gravity pulling blood down into the legs, blood redistributes into the head causing facial swelling. The inner ear, which normally controls our equilibrium on earth, is confused by the lack of gravity and many astronauts experience nausea and vomiting as a result. But more than anything else, the lack of normal "1g" gravity in space may limit human exploration of space because the under-use of muscles causes them to become weak and the progressive loss of calcium weakens bones also.1
			<br /><br />Data from long-duration microgravity exposure during Skylab missions in the 1970s indicated an average bone loss of 1% per month.2 To counter this decline, NASA required astronauts to perform regular exercise in orbit and dedicated space shuttle missions to the evaluation of vacuum gravity suits and treadmills. While helpful, exercise has not prevented bone-loss during space flight.3 In a sense, bones need gravity because they are designed to resist gravity and mechanical forces on earth. There is within bone a mechanism to sense where mechanical stress is placed on the bone and to call in bone-building cells to reinforce or "remodel" the bone. Since these design features are not needed in microgravity, the body switches from using dietary calcium to build bone, to leaching calcium from bone - thus reducing bone strength.4
			<br /><br />These concerns are not insurmountable. It may be that Arthur C. Clarke's vision of a circular, rotating spaceship, from the book and movie, 2001: A Space Odyssey, will need to be realized in order to create an artificial earth-like gravity field which we bring with us into space. In the end, these considerations should remind us that our earth environment and the needs of our human physiology are intelligently designed and constructed to be precisely matched and, while we may visit space, there is still no place like home.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnotes
			<br /><br />1. West JB. Physiology of a microgravity environment: Historical perspectives: Physiology in microgravity. Journal of Applied Physiology 89:379-384, 2000.
			<br />2. HolickMF. Perspectives on the impact of weightlessness on calcium and bone metabolism. Bone 22(5)105S-111S, 1998.
			<br />3. LeBlanc A et al. Future human bone research in space. Bone 22(5)113S-116S, 1998.
			<br />4. Burger EH and J Klein-Nulend. Microgravity and bone cell mechanosensitivity. Bone 22 (5)127S-130S, 1998.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="the-fingerprint-of-god">
		<title>The Fingerprint of God</title>
		<article>
			<img src="img/Fetus.jpg" />
			<em>With everything God touches He leaves something of His glory behind. </em>
			<br /><br />I recognize faces easily, although names are sometimes slow to come to mind. Just ask my children. Each is a unique person, and though I recognize them, I still occasionally mix up their names. What I never forget is that they are separate and distinct persons from me. Each is genetically complete, clearly human, and very much alive, both physically and spiritually. Some have suggested that personhood also depends on the presence of brain function, age from conception, or even location (inside or outside the womb). The definition of who is, and who is not, a person is literally a life and death distinction for unborn children. Since January of 1973, some 33 years ago now, millions of children have failed to meet the legal definition of personhood and have lost their lives from a horrible "choice" made by, of all people, their own mothers.
			<br /><br />The biological facts are well known. The human egg and sperm reproductive cells are both alive, but each is an incomplete cell because each contains half the normal amount of genetic material as a regular body cell. It is only when the sperm cell penetrates the outer defensive layer of the egg and the two cells fuse during fertilization that a genetically unique, diploid, human cell is formed. At that moment, a human genetic profile or fingerprint is established which is different from either parent and which never changes no matter how many trillion cells develop from this first cell. Fertilization, or conception, is the first moment a new, genetically unique human life can be recognized.
			<br /><br />Even more amazing is the evidence, developed in the past four decades, that the mother's immune system recognizes the growing embryo as a "foreign" object which should be rejected - just as a heart or skin transplant from another person would be rejected unless anti-rejection drugs were taken. But the growing baby, despite being recognized through its histocompatibility proteins as foreign, is not attacked as if it were just some tissue graft. Scientists call this situation an "immunological paradox" because mothers develop potentially lethal antibody and cell-mediated immune responses against the growing child but the response does not damage the infant.1 Instead, during pregnancy, a temporary state of immunological "tolerance" or protection develops which lasts until delivery of the child. The body recognizes the developing child as if it were an invading bacterial infection or an organ graft, but instead of removing this threat, the body protects this new life. It has been said that life began just once and since then is just passed on. The biological facts are clear that, for the individual, this point of "passing" is the moment of conception. Conception creates a new life, a new person. It is equally clear that God has finely and elegantly designed the mother's immune system to recognize, but also protect, the growing new life within her until birth. This is not an immunological paradox. It is the fingerprint of God.
			<br /><br />Written by Michael G. Windheuser, Ph.D.
			<br /><br />Endnote
			<br /><br />1 A.L. Mellor and D.H. Munn. Immunology at the maternalfetal interface: Lessons for T cell tolerance and suppression. Annual Review of Immunology 2000; 18:367-391.
		</article>
	</content>
	
	<content name="about-us">
		<title>About Us</title>
		<article>
			We are people from a variety of backgrounds who find the Bible worth taking seriously. Discovering the Lord Jesus as our Saviour was the best thing that ever happened to us. We want everyone we meet to get in on this too! We have found that the message of the Bible can provide a clarity and convincing certainty hard to find elsewhere.
			<br /><br />We are especially interested in helping others discover reality and richness in living through a personal relationship with God, the God who has made Himself knowable through His Word, the Bible. We seek to clear away misunderstandings about the Bible's message and to invite thinking people to take a serious look at the amazing claims and credentials of the Lord Jesus Christ.
			<br /><br />We have each found inner peace, certain hope, secure love, a way to make sense of our troubles, and the secret of true happiness in our lives. And because we have found all this through a personal relationship with Christ, you can understand why we highly recommend him!
			<br /><br />We find this promise from the Bible most encouraging: <em>God says, "And you will seek me and find me, when you search for me with all your heart" (Jeremiah 29:13)</em>.
		</article>
	</content>
</cms>